<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Medicina diastatica, or, Sympatheticall mumie containing many mysterious and hidden secrets in philosophy and physick, by the [brace] construction, extraction, transplantation and application [brace] of microcosmical &amp; spiritual mumie : teaching the magneticall cure of diseases at distance, &amp;c. / abstracted from the works of Dr. Theophr. Paracelsus by the labour and industry of Andrea Tentzelius ... ; translated out of the Latine by Ferdinando Parkhurst ...</title>
            <author>Paracelsus, 1493-1541.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28634</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3542</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41864</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19680548</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19680548</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109298</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28634)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109298)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1696:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Medicina diastatica, or, Sympatheticall mumie containing many mysterious and hidden secrets in philosophy and physick, by the [brace] construction, extraction, transplantation and application [brace] of microcosmical &amp; spiritual mumie : teaching the magneticall cure of diseases at distance, &amp;c. / abstracted from the works of Dr. Theophr. Paracelsus by the labour and industry of Andrea Tentzelius ... ; translated out of the Latine by Ferdinando Parkhurst ...</title>
                  <author>Paracelsus, 1493-1541.</author>
                  <author>Tentzel, Andreas.</author>
                  <author>Parkhurst, Ferdinando, fl. 1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 128 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Newcomb for T. Heath, and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine, Magic, mystic, and spagiric.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109298:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Medicina Diaſtatica</hi> OR Sympatheticall MUMIE: <hi>CONTAINING,</hi> Many myſterious and hidden Secrets In <hi>PHILOSOPHY</hi> and <hi>PHYSICK.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Conſtruction</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Extraction</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tranſplantation</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>and <hi>Application</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
of <hi>Microcoſmical</hi> &amp; <hi>Spiritual</hi> MUMIE.</p>
            <p>Teaching the <hi>Magneticall</hi> cure of Diſeaſes at Diſtance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Abſtracted from the Works of Dr. <hi>THEOPHR. PARACELS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S:</hi> By the labour and induſtry of <hi>Andrea Tentzelius,</hi> Phil. &amp; Med.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of the Latine</hi> BY FERDINANDO PARKHURST, Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Newcomb</hi> for <hi>T. Heath,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in <hi>Ruſſell-ſtreet,</hi> neer the <hi>Piazza's</hi> of <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:109298:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109298:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable <hi>Baſill</hi> Earle of <hi>Denbigh</hi> Viſcount <hi>Feilding</hi> and Baron of <hi>Newnham.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R Lordſhip ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſometime caſt your eye upon the <hi>Originall</hi> of this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> ſeemed to ratifie the credit it had received in the World by the <hi>honor</hi> of your Approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
<pb facs="tcp:109298:3"/>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the intimation whereof, I have (out of my eſpeciall Obligations to your Lordſhip) pretermitted my more peculiar Studies for the <hi>Tranſlation</hi> of this Peece Not that it could thereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the better acceptanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with your Lordſhip (where there is ſo much Language, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other accompliſhments of <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi>) but in reſpect of the thing it ſelf (a <hi>Myſterie</hi> of <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy</hi>) leſt it ſhould out-grow the better knowledge, as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hath the common Preſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:109298:3"/>My Lord, Theſe conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have chiefly induced the imployment of my beſt Ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours in the performance of this VVork, eſpecially the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of your Lordſhips Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection; under which confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence I have made it <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> as the least acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my duty to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or reſpects to the Generall Good: Which if it may receive the favour of your Lordſhips Countenance, I ſhall not doubt its <hi>preferment,</hi> and therein the advancement of the <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neticall Myſterie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:109298:4"/>I confeſſe, <hi>Subjects</hi> of this nature are not ſo uſually quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with that honor here as in forain parts, under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of <hi>Great Perſonages;</hi> yet is it not for want of Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, but rather of Reaſon, for
<q>Nobilis eſt ſolus, Virtute inſignis, &amp; Arte:</q>
which is more then demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive in your Lordſhip: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Dedication</hi> of this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> being Exemplified by the Author to ſeverall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of honour (and thoſe the moſt Eminent) I may hope your Lordſhip (as inferiour to
<pb facs="tcp:109298:4"/>
none) will vouchſafe me the priviledge to purſue my <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall:</hi> So may the defects of the <hi>Body</hi> be ſupplyed in the <hi>Countenance,</hi> while your Lo<hi rend="sup">ps.</hi> favour ſhall Patronize both, by a diſpenſation or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of theſe my Ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors, to the future Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble Serv. FERD. PARK HURST.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:109298:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109298:5"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The Tranſlator to the Reader.</head>
            <p>THE Philoſopher contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plating the life of Man, would have <hi>Homo animalibus ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientius eſſe,</hi> man to be wiſer then all other creatures; I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it is the part of a wiſe man ſo to be, but how to be ſo every creature may direct: for though reaſon be appropriated to Man, ſenſe is as common to Animals, who by inſtinct have learned the knowledge of their own preſervation without our <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> of Reaſon; and by certain demonſtrations (as) from the <hi>Liberall Sciences</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> doe daily teach us that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or Art of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> diſputing <hi>Nature,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:109298:6"/>
the commanding <hi>Empereſſe</hi> of all Learning according to <hi>Menander;</hi>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </q>
So that mans reaſon eſpecially being prompted by the <hi>oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> will conclude him no leſſe then what he is, <hi>(viz)</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>Compendium</hi> of <hi>her ſelf,</hi> or the very <hi>centre,</hi> in which all the rayes and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of her Sphear do meet.</p>
            <p>And thus from the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and conjunction of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> a new <hi>faculty</hi> is created, called <hi>Art;</hi> whoſe ſublime and ſubtle qualities in emulation of her <hi>Progenitrices,</hi> are drawn from her own <hi>principles; Ars imitari Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae ſolertian poteſt:</hi> from whence it conſequently appears, that, both <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite
<pb facs="tcp:109298:6"/>
in the work of <hi>perfection.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Neque Natura ſine arte ſufficit cutquam omnino quocunque in ſtudio; Nec Ars per ſe ſine praeſidio Naturae.</q>
            <p>Through this Coadjutorſhip and on <hi>Concatenation,</hi> are all things governed under the Title of <hi>Providence,</hi> by whoſe <hi>Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> Man eſpecially contributing in obedience, is not only prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, but alſo his ſelf-preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſecurity ſealed to him under that <hi>Magna Charta, Homo Naturae obediens homini nocere non poteſt,</hi> Man obeying the Lawes of <hi>Nature,</hi> can neither hurt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf nor prejudice another; This is no rigid Law, but a Rule in Equity, nay rather a gentle pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of an indulgent Mother, that <hi>Mater rerum omnium</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:109298:7"/>
Philoſophers ſo much adore.</p>
            <p>When therefore (by <hi>omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Providence) Nature, Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Art,</hi> with all their faculties conſpire together for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of mankinde, as the greateſt miracle of the world; what ſtupid Nature, would not in reaſon ſtudy that myſterious Art, wherein the life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of our ſelves depend?</p>
            <p>Wherefore I ſhall here (by way of Preſident) preſent thee with an <hi>Abſtract</hi> from that moſt learned Philoſopher <hi>Theophra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus Paracelſus,</hi> who (out of the conſiderations aforeſaid) did not only ſearch into the moſt occult and ſecret c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſes of <hi>Nature,</hi> but alſo (being well experimented by his own Art &amp; Practiſe made
<pb facs="tcp:109298:7"/>
them publick to the world in his <hi>Tract de Tempore ſeu Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia</hi>) Which piece (being illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by <hi>Andrea Tentzelius,</hi> Dr. in <hi>Philoſophy</hi> and <hi>Phyſick</hi>) I may here prefer as an <hi>Epitome</hi> of the moſt abſtruſe part of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſophy,</hi> treating of many hidden Myſteries and operations, in the rare and admirable cure of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes at diſtance, by <hi>tranſplanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> into other <hi>ſpecies,</hi> through a <hi>Mumiall</hi> and <hi>Magneticall</hi> power, drawn chiefly from the <hi>Sympathy</hi> and <hi>Antipathy</hi> of natural things.</p>
            <p>This excellent piece, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to my acquaintance by the favour of a worthy <hi>friend,</hi> my reſpects could not leſſe then ſalute him with a <hi>gratulor adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> at the firſt ſight; Afterward
<pb facs="tcp:109298:8"/>
finding him (as) a compleat <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman</hi> by his language in the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> tongue (though of <hi>Germane</hi> parents) and moſt accompliſht in his <hi>ſubject</hi> and <hi>matter,</hi> (being therewith ſo much affected) I could not in diſcharge of my ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations to my <hi>friend,</hi> (upon his requeſt) my own ſatisfaction, and the good will I bear to generall <hi>Learning,</hi> but diſcover his true <hi>worth</hi> and <hi>intrinſecal</hi> vertues to a more publique <hi>Surveigh;</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as <hi>providence</hi> had tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him into our own Country, ſo have my endeavours <hi>tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> him into our own Tongue; wherein (Gentle Reader) if he do not ſo clearly expreſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, the defects are mine, but if thou underſtand him not, the errour is thine.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:109298:8"/>In the <hi>Originall</hi> (beſides the difficulty of the ſubject) the long-breathed <hi>Periods,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny imperfect <hi>Parentheſes,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the common eſcapes of the Preſſe, would require a good Maſter in the laborious work of <hi>Tranſlation,</hi> and as diligent an Artiſt in correcting the <hi>Errata's.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as my greateſt care hath not been wanting in the compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the leaſt ſcruple, ſo I hope (without the eſcapes of the Printer, or the Readers Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) my endeavours may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a due <hi>Conſtruction:</hi> yet where a ſtrictneſſe of capacity cannot reach the <hi>Latitude</hi> of this <hi>(Magneticall) Sphere,</hi> ſuch may happily be <hi>eclipſed</hi> in the <hi>whole</hi> by the interpoſition of their
<pb facs="tcp:109298:9"/>
               <hi>parts,</hi> while the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous to thoſe of another <hi>Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deficiences</hi> of this Nature are moſt contingent in a ſelf opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which is, (for the moſt part) either ſo blinded by igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or hoodwinckt by conceit, that they dare not inquire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their own knowledge, leaſt by diſcovering themſelves they ſhould forfeit <hi>that</hi> which they only pretend to; <hi>Theſe</hi> of all others I deſire not to meet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, but if it be my fate, I wiſh they would begin where — Here I cloſe,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>It is wiſdome to learn that which a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man nòt know<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>June,</hi> 24. 1653.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Ferd. Parkhurſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:109298:9"/>
            <head>On his worthy Friend Mr. <hi>Parkhurst</hi> and his Tranſlation of this <hi>Mumiall Treatiſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis <hi>Rare Piece</hi> (treating of the wonderful effects to be wrought by <hi>Mumie</hi>) I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend unto this <hi>Nation,</hi> inviting the Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Readers hereof, unto a due acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>learned Tranſlators</hi> induſtry; Who, having met with ſo Crabbed a <hi>Latine Author,</hi> ſuch tedious <hi>Parentheſes</hi> therein, words ſo ambiguous and inſignificant, yet hath he very judiciouſly and dexteriouſly overcome thoſe <hi>difficulties,</hi> and rendered his <hi>Author</hi> in a perfect intelligible and pleaſant <hi>Engliſh ſtyle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Subject</hi> he Treats of, is <hi>Sublime</hi> and high (if not the greateſt <hi>Myſtery</hi> known to mortall Man,) be thou therefore thankfull who ſhalt read it; and learn, rather to admire then deſpiſe the wonderfull works of the <hi>Almighty,</hi> although unto thee they may ſeem <hi>Clouded.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>William Lilly</hi> Student in Aſtrology.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <gap reason="missing" resp="#UOM" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:109298:10"/>
            <head>To his ingenious Friend Mr. <hi>Ferdinando Parkhurſt</hi> the induſtrious Tranſlator of this Excellent Treatiſe.</head>
            <l>
               <hi>PHyſicians</hi> need no more their Trade advance,</l>
            <l>By tedious, fulſome long Receits and chance;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Here</hi> they may meet a neerer ſurer way;</l>
            <l>Which will their tedious Fallacies diſplay,</l>
            <l>And ſhew, what <hi>Nature,</hi> when diſcovered, can</l>
            <l>Work in the body of imperfect Man;</l>
            <l>By meanes ſo eaſy, and ſo ſecret, that</l>
            <l>They ſlily order and direct our fate.</l>
            <l>So what great <hi>Paracelſus</hi> ſearching minde,</l>
            <l>Led by a higher <hi>Genius,</hi> firſt did finde,</l>
            <l>And what <hi>Tentzelius</hi> did from him diſplay,</l>
            <l>Scattering his <hi>clouds</hi> and ſhewing brighter day;</l>
            <l>We (being made ſharers of ſuch wealth) muſt owe</l>
            <l>(Since you h've given it to th' Engliſh World) to <hi>you</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Whoſe worthy care hath now brought home this <hi>peece,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And with it given us a <hi>Golden Fleece.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Roger Ellis</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr>.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:109298:10"/>
            <head>To my honored friend Mr. <hi>Ferdinando Parkhurſt</hi> Tranſlator of this <hi>Magneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> Tract.</head>
            <l>MY deareſt <hi>Friend</hi> ſuch is thy worthineſſe,</l>
            <l>That nothing but thine owne can <hi>thee</hi> expreſſe;</l>
            <l>What ever <hi>Learning, Wit,</hi> or <hi>Art,</hi> can teach,</l>
            <l>Is comprehended <hi>all</hi> within the reach</l>
            <l>Of thy <hi>capacity;</hi> for who can ſay</l>
            <l>Thou art not read in <hi>All,</hi> although ſome may</l>
            <l>Expoſe their <hi>Genius</hi> more to publick ſight;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Thy modeſty conceales what others write.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>While <hi>Learning</hi> languiſheth, thou doeſt <hi>Tranſlate</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Great <hi>Paracelſus</hi> from his firſt Eſtate</l>
            <l>Into thy Native Country, and there land him</l>
            <l>Safe to all thoſe that rightly underſtand him;</l>
            <l>But let your <hi>Mountebanck, Leech, Quak,</hi> and thoſe</l>
            <l>That deal in <hi>Simples,</hi> and their common <hi>Doſe,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Keep to their <hi>Simples</hi> ſtill; for <hi>ignorance</hi> ſure</l>
            <l>Can nere aſſume <hi>thy</hi> true <hi>Magnetick cure.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>P. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <gap reason="missing" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ pages">
               <desc>〈2… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:109298:11"/>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 7.</hi> Of the uſe of <hi>Spirituall Mumie</hi> (in generall.)</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 8.</hi> Of the favour of the <hi>Heavens</hi> towards the aforeſaid operations.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 9.</hi> Of the time deſtined by the <hi>Heavens</hi> for the propoſed operations.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 10.</hi> Of the uſe of <hi>Spiritual Mumie (in ſpecie)</hi> and firſt to reconcile a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip between two men.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 11.</hi> To reconcile private or publick <hi>Enemies.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 12.</hi> To reconcile the <hi>Ape</hi> and <hi>Serpent</hi> (naturally hating one another) and other <hi>Animals,</hi> who are by nature enemies.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 13.</hi> To procure a mutuall love and affection betwixt a <hi>Man</hi> and his <hi>Wife.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 14.</hi> Of the operation of <hi>Antipathy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 15.</hi> To cure both kinds of <hi>Jaundles.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 16.</hi> To cure the <hi>Dropſie</hi> Magneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 17.</hi> Of the <hi>Pluriſie,</hi> and of curing inward <hi>Impoſtumations Sympatheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 18.</hi> To cure <hi>Feavers Magnetically.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 19.</hi> Of the oppilations of the <hi>Liver,
<pb facs="tcp:109298:11"/>
Spleen, Brain, Lungs, Reynes,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 20.</hi> Of <hi>Aches</hi> in the <hi>Joynts</hi> and <hi>Limbes,</hi> by reaſon of oppilation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 21.</hi> Of the <hi>Podegra,</hi> and <hi>Catarrhs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 22.</hi> Of <hi>Wounds</hi> and <hi>Ulcers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 23.</hi> Of the <hi>Hernia,</hi> or <hi>Burſtenneſſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 24.</hi> Of <hi>Fluxions,</hi> and <hi>Salt Rheums</hi> hurtfull to the Teeth and Eyes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 25.</hi> Of <hi>Menſtruous</hi> Evacuations and Retention.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 26.</hi> Of the <hi>Conſumption</hi> and <hi>Hectick.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 27.</hi> Of particular <hi>Blaſtings.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 28.</hi> Of <hi>Sterility</hi> or <hi>Barrenneſſe;</hi> and alſo the manner of detracting ſtrength from an Horſe and communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it to a man; or from any man or Beaſt, and tranſmitting it into any other.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:109298:12"/>
            <head>Reader.</head>
            <p>IF theſe my <hi>Endeavours</hi> may receive a due conſtruction from thee, thou wilt thereby clear thy own judgment and encourage my future intendments of a ſecond Tract, <hi>viz. Of the naturall reaſon of the</hi> Tree <hi>of</hi> Life, <hi>and of</hi> Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>of</hi> Good <hi>and</hi> Evill. And alſo of the myſticall interpretation of that great ſecret, <hi>viz Cabaliſticall concordancy of</hi> Life <hi>and</hi> Death; Chriſt <hi>and</hi> Adam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Likewiſe many other Pieces both <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophicall</hi> and <hi>Mathematicall:</hi> As alſo of the <hi>Sciences</hi> in generall, under the title of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are now preparing for the Preſſe, by the ſtudies and induſtrie of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Friend <hi>F. Parkhurst.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109298:12"/>
            <head>A MUMIALL TREATISE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the definition, diverſitie, conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nature, and property of <hi>Mumie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing now upon the Treatiſe of <hi>Mumie,</hi> I conceive it moſt proper firſt to ſhew what is commonly underſtood by <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie,</hi> and what is meant by the ſame in this place.</p>
               <p>Mumie, from the <hi>Arabians</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is generally denoted by the Phyſicians and Apothecaries under theſe foure kindes, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Arabian.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Aegyptian.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Piſſaſphaltos.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Lybian.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:109298:13"/>1. <hi>Arabian</hi> Mumie, is a certain compoſitio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Aloes, Myrrhe, Croco's, and Balſamum, with which they doe (uſually) embalme dead bodies; which (after a while being taken out of the ſepulchres) with the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies or matter ſweating forth from the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daver, is preſerved and kept for Phyſicall uſes.</p>
               <p>Thus much <hi>Rhaſes</hi> affirmeth (in his <hi>Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymis</hi>) ſaying, <hi>Mumie</hi> is a thing which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> found in the earth, where the bodies of the dead embalmed with Aloes are intombed, and the humours of the Cadaver is reſolved with the mixture of the Aloes: <hi>Serapis</hi> his Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter teſtifieth the ſame, <hi>chap.</hi> 283. who writeth, that <hi>Mumie</hi> of the Sepulchres i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from the humidity of an humane body, intermixt and incorporated with Aloe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Myrrhe, and other ingredients.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Mumie, is tranſported from <hi>Aegypt</hi> to us, which is not made of any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies embalmed with Aloes and Myrrhe, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (ſo termed by the <hi>Greeks</hi>) which is a kinde of fat clay or ſulphury matter of an aereal and fiery quality:) For as the Nobility did uſe Croco's, Aloes Myrrhe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for Embalmings, whoſe bodie (as <hi>Scaliger</hi> reports) was death to dig up (ſo as <hi>Strabo</hi> writes) the dead bodies o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the common people were uſually embal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109298:13"/>
with <hi>Aſphaltos,</hi> to keep and preſerve them from corruption.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Piſſaſphaltos,</hi> (by the <hi>Greeks</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>pix,</hi> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>bitumen</hi>) is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of a pitchy and ſulphury matter; or rather, this <hi>Mumie</hi> is a ſubſtance retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſame virtues which <hi>Diaſcorides</hi> attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes to <hi>Piſſaſphaltos,</hi> having the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects as <hi>Bitumen</hi> mingled with pitch; but in the mean while we get not the true <hi>Mumie,</hi> and very rarely the <hi>Piſſaſphaltos</hi> of <hi>Dioſcori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des;</hi> but there is a counterfeit Confection of Pitch and <hi>Bitumen</hi> commonly ſold for <hi>Piſſaſphaltos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Lybian</hi> Mumie (is ſo called in reſpect of the place from whence it is) <hi>viz.</hi> for in the Region of <hi>Hammon</hi> being a part of <hi>Lybia,</hi> which is between the Countrey of <hi>Cyrene</hi> and <hi>Alexandria</hi> are many Quickſands raiſed by impetuous and turbulent whirle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winds, by which meanes the unwary Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers are oftentimes ſwallowed up, and ſo through the obvolution and rowling of the mountainous ſands are ſoon par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and dryed by the heat of the Sun; the fleſh thus ſcorched with the humane bones, is brought away without any commixtures or other embalmings: (which is he Mumie here meant.)</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:109298:14"/>Wherefore it evidently appears, that there are four common ſorts of <hi>Mumie;</hi> ſo that <hi>Fuchius</hi> is not a little miſtaken, in <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Paradox.</hi> 40. <hi>cap.</hi> when hee endevours to make <hi>Serapio</hi> contradict himſelfe, and <hi>Avi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen</hi> and <hi>Rhaſes</hi> to oppoſe themſelves, and the whole Sect of <hi>Arabians;</hi> making <hi>Piſſaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaltos</hi> (in ſome places uſed for <hi>Mumie</hi>) the onely <hi>Mumie,</hi> excluding all other.</p>
               <p>Although theſe kindes of <hi>Mumie</hi> are eſteemed very advantagious for the curing of green wounds, ruptures, and bruiſes; yet in the proſecution of this Treatiſe, will appear the danger of adminiſtring the <hi>Mumie</hi> of any body promiſcuouſly, for that <hi>Mumie</hi> is alwayes moſt neceſſarily to be avoyded, that is not certainly known to be collected from an wholſome and ſound body.</p>
               <p>Wherefore <hi>Theophraſtus Paracelſus</hi> upon this ſubject adds a fift ſort of <hi>Mumie, viz.</hi> that which is extracted from ſome perfect body, not dying of any naturall diſeaſe, but of ſome violent death; upon the reaſons following.</p>
               <p>For as by <hi>divine ordination</hi> no edible Creature was to be ſlain for mans food, but ſuch as was perfectly ſound, and free from diſeaſes, leſt with the decoction of the meat, we ſhould receive the diſea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:109298:14"/>
into us; much leſſe ſhould any thing that dyeth naturally be for internall uſe, or taken for nouriſhment, when as the ſame death or diſeaſe that accompanyed it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, might afterward enſue. And this is generally manifeſted by all Creatures of Prey, as</p>
               <p>Amongſt
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Birds</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Beaſts</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fiſhes</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
the
<list>
                     <item>Kite, Eagle, Hawke,</item>
                     <item>Lyon, Wolfe, Fox Bear,</item>
                     <item>Cungre, Dolphin, Tuny, Mullet,</item>
                  </list>
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe, and many other Animals, that affect and live on Prey, (except the Bear by chance,) will not feed on, or any wayes touch Carrion, unleſſe meer hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger compell them; the reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they doe not onely nouriſh and increaſe their owne bodies by the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of their Prey, but alſo their owne Mumie by their ſpirituall Mumie, which doth for the moſt part evaporate with a naturall expiration of the living Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>From whence it is apparent, that if we could feed on living Creatures, and digeſt, alter, and ſubdue the matter, it would bee much more conducible to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109298:15"/>
the nouriſhing and preſervation of our bodies and ſpirits: For as freſh fleſh which is tender, is more wholeſome then that which is praemacerated, and corrupt, having more vitality; ſo conſequently, that which is ſound, and vivacious, is more nutrimentall then any which a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe hath killed, and thereby deprived it of its ſpirit or <hi>Mumie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For thus through the harmonies and commiſſures of the parts kept ſound, and clean, may be extracted the virtues and faculties of things more entirely, then otherwiſe by opening and extending the moſt occult and internall parts, which cauſeth evaporation: This is experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Troglodites or Hedge ſparrow, ſeaſoned with pepper and ſalt, and eaten raw by any one troubled with the Stone, it hath an eminent faculty of breaking or diſſolving the ſame, which being boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led or otherwiſe prepared, loſeth that effect.</p>
               <p>Another reaſon may be here given, that nothing can be proper for food, unleſſe that which is alible and vitall, becauſe our life and ſpirit cannot be otherwiſe ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, then by the Analogicall and vitall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of another. Neither can the ſubſtance of our body be ſupported, without the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109298:15"/>
materiality of ſome other; wherefore thoſe creatures that feed and live on the wholeſomeſt things, are moſt nutrimentall for us. Moreover every part cheriſheth and affecteth it ſelf with a certain delectation;</p>
               <p>For through a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſympathy our
<list>
                     <item>Brains</item>
                     <item>Lungs</item>
                     <item>Liver</item>
                     <item>Heart</item>
                  </list>
is nouriſhed by the like in other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>Now as <hi>Theophr. Paracelſus</hi> delivers, this <hi>Mumie</hi> can no where be more truly had, then from the bodies of criminall perſons (<hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as violently ſuffered death by ſtrangu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, as on Gibbets, &amp;c.) For from ſuch there is a gentle ſiccation that expungeth the watery humour, without deſtroying the oyle and ſpirituall, which is cheriſhed by the heavenly Luminaries, and ſtrengthened continually by the affluence and appulſes of the celeſtiall Spirits; whence it may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be called by the name of Conſtellated, or Celeſtiall Mumie.</p>
               <p>Wherefore <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> preferreth this Aereall ſpirit (or <hi>Mumie</hi>) before all other corporeall <hi>Mumies,</hi> either of fire, water, or earth; which may chiefly be obſerved from his own words in the <hi>Germane</hi> Tongue, as followeth; —</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:109298:16"/>
                  <hi>Benn die Arkte und ſonſt manniglich wu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten, was mit dieſer <hi>Mumia</hi> furzunehmen, oder wozu ſie nuke, wurdekein Bbelthater uber drey Lag am Dalgen oder auffdem Rade liegen bleiben, ſondern hinweg genommen, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> es anders muglich were</hi> (that is) If Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans or any other body underſtood but the right uſe of this <hi>Mumie,</hi> or what it is good for, not any Malefactors would be left three daies on the Gallowes, or conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue on the Wheel, from being ſtoln away; for they would run any hazard for procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of theſe Bodies.</p>
               <p>Now <hi>Paracelſus</hi> doth not ſpeak only of this, but alſo of another ſpirituall <hi>Mumie</hi> produced and derived from thence, (though ſomewhat obſcurely) in theſe words: <hi>Daſs noch eine audere <hi>Mumie</hi> verhanden, nemblich die, welche bon einem lebendigen Leibe</hi> ſeparirt <hi>und</hi> praepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rirt <hi>wird. Dann ein jeglicher Menſch kan ſeinen Leib</hi> in Mumiam tranſmutirn, <hi>ſoinem Leib und Leiben ohne ſcaden, und ein Stuk bon ſeim Leib nehmen daſs mans doch dem Leib nicht an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſihet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is yet another <hi>Mumie,</hi> namely, that which is taken from a living bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſeparated and prepared accordingly,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109298:16"/>
for any ones body may be tranſmuted into Mumie, without prejudice either to the body or the life thereof, and the body ſhall be no whit the worſe for it, neither ſhall it be diſcerned that any ſuch thing hath been done there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
               <p>Therefore I ſhall further explain what <hi>Paracelſus</hi> meaneth by <hi>corporeall</hi> and <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Mumie,</hi> and what is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by it.</p>
               <p>Now it is to be obſerved, that it is called Corporeall <hi>Mumie,</hi> not by reaſon of its formall exiſtent part, as that it is ſo in and by its ſelf naturally, for there is no Mumie properly but ſpirituall, or only in the ſame reſpect; becauſe from the deſtruction and diſſipation of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit or vitall Balſome, the defect of all true Mumie may be argued, the body in the mean while no waies ſuffring: but ſo called in reſpect of its ſubſiſtence and operation, as it may be inherent to the body, as well by its ſelf as by its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, and advance its power and effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, according to the <hi>oeconomie</hi> and order of the Artiſt, no otherwiſe then by, and with the ſame body.</p>
               <p>As therefore you may ſee from the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor it is improperly called <hi>corporeall,</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:109298:17"/>
ſo likewiſe he doth not only call it ſpiritual <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> according to its <hi>ens</hi> or being, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, according to its relation, becauſe it keepeth ſtill and effecteth its intended ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, both beyond and without its cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreall ſubject, even by the emanation of the virtue of the <hi>Mumie</hi> only, as the accident from the ſubject; ſo ſpirituall <hi>Mumie</hi> is here ſo properly called by <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> becauſe properly and ſubſtantially it is not ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Mumie,</hi> but only the property of it. For how can the ſpirit have any divorcement or ſeparation from the body, if this be not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo divided? Or would not ſome violent exerciſe, motion, Phyſick, or opening a vein, by which the ſpirit evaporates, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure an eminent danger, and irrecoverable loſſe of it?</p>
               <p>From hence we do not determine truly and Philoſophically, the corporeity and ſpirituality of <hi>Mumie</hi> according to the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall difference of it aforeſaid, but only to ſpeak of it in reſpect of its ſubſiſtence and medicinall uſe, or in reſpect of its profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſpenſation, which would otherwiſe require ſeverall denominations; for the Phyſician doth not diſtinguiſh <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curately, but for the moſt part <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latively, and ſo ſtates and defines the Animall, Vitall, and Naturall Spirits in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109298:17"/>
man; which notwithſtanding are but ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n a certain comparation. For as the ſeed of man is neither part of the man, nor any ſubſtantiall of the parts of the ſame body, but only a power or certain form deſcending into the Teſticles, with the moſt refined and ſubtile matter of the alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall ſuperfluity, by whoſe (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) or ſpermaticall proclivity it is afterwards more exactly decocted, and augmented by the mechanick and ſubordinate ſpirits, and is endued with a multiplying faculty of it ſelf in the place and time appointed by the Liturgie and rule of Nature. So ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall <hi>Mumie,</hi> in ſo much as it under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goeth the work of Tranſplantation; (ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ought to be performed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any detriment of the body,) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be part of the internall <hi>Mumie,</hi> much leſſe of the body it ſelfe; but muſt of neceſſity be a kinde of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, addition or trajection, which wholly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes of the faculties, and properties of the internall principle; and ſo being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, diſſipates its ſelf, not only amongſt the utmoſt parts of the body, but even into the beſt diſpoſed matter, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covereth the ſame virtues as if the very principle and ſubſtance of the <hi>Mumie</hi> were every where preſent (throughly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109298:18"/>
diſſipated) which vertue doth reſemble that which is appropriated to the <hi>Magnet</hi> or Loadſtone: for after the ſame manner the ſoul diſpoſeth it ſelf into the alimentall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of new matter; for as the flame of one lamp tranſmigrateth into another, and yet remaineth intire, ſo likewiſe doth the Rayes or beams iſſue out of the body and although it be ſomething of, or per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taining to the body, yet it is not the body it ſelf, nor any part of it.</p>
               <p>From hence it may evidently appear that <hi>Theophr. Paracelſus</hi> called Spirituall <hi>Mumie</hi> its ſelf, and its geniture (as I may term it) by one and the ſame name, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly fitteth it for Tranſplantation: The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> conſiderations being had will anticipate many doubts and errors which might o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe happen in the enſuing Treatiſe</p>
               <p>This premiſed, we come now to the definition of the thing it ſelf; <q>
                     <hi>Mumie</hi> properly ſo called is the moſt ſubtile ſubſtance of the body, Spirituall, Aethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, and in reſpect of its Nature and ſpecies coingenited, permanent in ſome meaſure both in and after death, retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for the moſt part both its affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and internall and ſpeciall virtues, wonderfully diffuſive of its ſelf and is qualities by means of its extracted and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109298:18"/>
conſtellated Tranſplantation, to the end the unſound and viciated diſpoſition may be rectified, and the uncorrupted and perfect be preſerved and ſtrengthned.</q>
               </p>
               <p>We may inſtance many examples before us of this <hi>Mumie,</hi> notwithſtanding one or two I hope may be ſufficient in this place, taken partly from another kinde, from whence we may gather its wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full operation.</p>
               <p>There is a proper aliment or food ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for every kinde of Creature, as certain flies feed on the leaves of Napell, by ſome called Wolfebane; Hemlock, which is poyſonous to man, is nouriſhing to the bird called the Starling; and the hearb Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebore that is noxious to men, is food for the Quaile. Moreover every part of the body doth accommodate it ſelf, and hath its exiſtency from its moſt proper nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; as the bone by the bony ſubſtance, the fleſh by the fleſhy is preſerved and augmented; which is no other then the quality and propriety of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>Mumie,</hi> which requireth the proper <hi>Mumie</hi> of another for the conſervation of it ſelf, accommodating and applying it to its own uſe. This is experienced in the Phthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick (or Conſumption of the Lungs) which is cured by uſing and eating the Lungs of a Fox
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:109298:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
or the alteration of them; and is truly of the ſame <hi>proſapiae</hi> (deſcent) or nature of thoſe things which we here treat of.</p>
               <p>So a grain of Corn caſt into the Earth putrifyeth, and as it were periſheth before it putteth forth a new ſtem; where is here the Anatome and ſpirit of the ſeed, which after by a new revolution adorneth the worldly Theatre with a new body? Wherefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> may without all doubt call that which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth the ſeminall and procreative faculty, Mumie truly Balſamick (or <hi>ſpirituall</hi>) ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogeneall with the Humane <hi>Mumie</hi> before mentioned, the divine principle of all ſecret operations of every naturall thing.</p>
               <p>The ſame may be ſaid of the ſeed of man, in which though very little (for that which is viſible is not the ſeed) yet the whole man with all his properties, faculties, actions, and paſſions doth in the firſt act acquieſce.</p>
               <p>It is likewiſe true of hearbs, plants and other things, being pluckt up and dryed, or in any wiſe dead; whereof there are many kinds, in which notwithſtanding the ſame virtue as was at firſt infuſed into them do remain and operate. As there is in every root of Poeony gathered in a Mumiall and proper time an <hi>Antepilepticall</hi> faculty, or preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the falling ſickneſſe, (for it is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:109298:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in vain that the ſame hearb hath diverſe virtues, it being from the diverſe ſeed, and Celite or infuſed <hi>Mumie,</hi> of which we have given an inſtance or two in our <hi>Philoſopho Medico de Peſte,</hi> or <hi>the Philoſophicall Phyſician or Cure of the Plague</hi>) ſo in other hearbs remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the like virtue till their <hi>Mumie</hi> is wholly extinguiſhed; as,</p>
               <p>In
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ivie,</hi> a virtue Artheticall to preſerve from the Gout.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Scordium,</hi> a virtue againſt the Gangrene.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Scabios,</hi> againſt peſtilentiall tumors.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Gallopſis</hi> againſt the Cancer.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>To what other thing may we attribute this, that ſometimes in one and the ſame thing there are diverſe, and many times con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary faculties, unleſſe to the various con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe of <hi>Mumie</hi> from diverſe ſpecies, which ſometimes conferre diverſe faculties, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times weakly diſpoſing, and othertimes wholly changing: Thus the weed <hi>Cuſcuta</hi> or <hi>Dodder,</hi> (which from its windings about <hi>Thyme,</hi> is called <hi>Epithymum</hi> (or <hi>Thymeweed</hi>) hath far other virtue in it then that which groweth or twineth about other hearbs or plants. Harts-horne hath different qualities from the Bucks-horn; the Sea-horſe-tooth from the teeth of an Elephant; the Oake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109298:20"/>
from that of the Holly, ſo the Gals of other wood from thoſe of the Oake. What other cauſe hath the contagion of diſeaſes? according to the verſe,
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cum ſpectant oculi laeſos, laedantur &amp; ipſi;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>While they behold the ſoreneſſe of an eye</l>
                     <l>Their own infected are (by Sympathie.)</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>For ſuch as any mans conſtitution is, ſuch is his Mumie, ſuch is his expiration, and ſuch is the reception and tranſplantation Analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gically in another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> It may be objected from hence, that then all diſeaſes would be infectious from every ones <hi>Mumie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer, All are contagious, eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> health it ſelf, if we conſider it only according to its proper active faculty, or (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) its <hi>perfection</hi> (as the Philoſophers terme it): for every thing naturally is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with a power of affecting another thing with its own qualities, although every operation is not equally effectuall; for <hi>Sanity</hi> is a certain quieſcency, temperament and ſerenity favorable to Nature; and ſo o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> leſſe activity, then that the ſuborned <hi>Mumie</hi> of it ſhould aptly or readily affect either the ſound or diſeaſed (body): Which reaſon may likewiſe be given for many diſeaſes not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109298:20"/>
commonly infectious; for either they are more deeply radicated in the body, and are diſpoſed to a fixed coagulation, or elſe they are leſſe powerfull in their ſpirits then to communicate infection, though never ſo neer or alter the ſubſtance notwithſtanding their contact. Although none of theſe in reſpect of contagion are every where deſtructive <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> according to their efficacy and the paſſive ſtate of the object, but <hi>(ſecundum magis &amp; minus)</hi> according to more and leſſe all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes are contagious; ſo that we ſee in al theſe things that <hi>Mumie</hi> is the principal cauſe. To theſe we might eaſily add many other things which do viciſſively affect or abhorre each other, (by a <hi>ſympatheticall</hi> and <hi>antipatheticall</hi> diſpoſition) whoſe ſpirituall <hi>Mumie</hi> is the principal Agent and wonderful Arthitectrix of their moſt ſecret operations.</p>
               <p>Now this very <hi>Mumie</hi> being according to its ſelf entire, and according to the parts and individuall properties of them (which is but the parts otherwiſe conditioned and related to their ſpecies) is ſo cloſely (and ſecretly) joyned by a peculiar <hi>influence,</hi> as the whole Kingdom and Monarchy of Nature doth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably abound with conſentaneous and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſentaneous, <hi>ſympatheticall</hi> and <hi>antipatheticall influences,</hi> that in whatſoever part or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty any wiſe divided from it, it will be
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109298:21"/>
united to it in a more noble degree, the whole by a kind of divine right of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, as in a man that which is part of the head ſympathizeth with the head, and of the feet with the feet, will admirably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire and conſociate to that common victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſpirit of the World; and the ſame whole will ſympathize by a Magnetick power with good or bad either <hi>philema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically</hi> or <hi>plagetically</hi> at the greateſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
               <p>This appeares by that true ſympathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguent,</hi> and that there are naturall cauſes not only of this but of many other the like things, (without any ſuſpicion of <hi>Magick</hi>) Nature its liberall mother doth dayly confirme by many experiments; amongſt the reſt (which may worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be remembred) the conſervation of the vitall ſpirit, from the appul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the generall ſpirit of the whole World; which according to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution by the definite coitions or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions of the ſtars and planets, whoſe influences abundantly operating do argue a <hi>ſynaphthis</hi> and contact of, and with the Planets in theſe things. In its <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or appearance, only part of the <hi>Mumie</hi> of the Wound (and that very little) adhere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to the weapon, yet being cleanſed with the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109298:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
unguent, communicates the whole acquiſited cure by a ſympatheticall virtue flowing from the animall and vitall ſpirit of the <hi>Mumie,</hi> to its Conſociate or ſyngennicall faculty in the veines of the very member through the ſudden mediation of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or great ſpirit of the World, which penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and extendeth all things; ſo as the curing of the part of <hi>Mumie</hi> in the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo is the redintegration and recovery of the whole <hi>Mumie</hi> in the part wounded; and contrarywiſe, the affliction or malady of the ſame cleaving to the Inſtrument, is the trouble and pain of the ſame in the wounded man.</p>
               <p>From which kind of <hi>ſympathy</hi> I preſume it proceeds that the careleſſe burying of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>ſecundine</hi> (pertaining to women in Childbed) and of other things <hi>(excremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum item alvinorum, &amp;c.)</hi> parts of the Mumie it ſelf, being individuall, do by unskilfull and ill uſage preſently endanger the whole <hi>individuum.</hi> So the <hi>zenith</hi> of a young maiden caſt into the fire, is ſaid to ſtay the fire, but with damage to the Virgin, becauſe it ought to periſh. To which may be added that old wines work a new in the veſſel, their Lees riſe and are troubled at the ſame time, when the Vines ſpring and ſhoot forth their branches.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:109298:22"/>This <hi>Anempodeſticall</hi> virtue (being of the ſame inclination and condition of <hi>Mumie</hi> flowing in the very ſtars or genius of things as in a kind of center) may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and truely ſaid to be the cauſe of all manner of ſtrange and wonderfull <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathies,</hi> as of occult and Magneticall cures, of Plants ſpringing and budding at the ſame time in ſundry places of the ſame Climate, bloſſoming and bringing forth fruit, and other the like effects: of which there are many examples obvious, ſhewing the true and adequate cauſes.</p>
               <p>For by what reaſon, when one <hi>Heliotropium</hi> turning towards the beams of the Sun, ſhould all other of the ſame kinde do the like? and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one <hi>Lote</hi> erecting it ſelf from the bottom of the water at the riſing and ſetting of the Sun, all other kinds of <hi>Trefoile</hi> in the ſame <hi>Hemiſphere</hi> move in the like manner by the fame virtue? Or whence cometh it to paſſe, that many which are born in the <hi>Novilune</hi> or new of the Moon have en equall impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency and imbecillity either in their bodies or mindes? Or from whence is it (as <hi>Mizaldus</hi> obſerveth) that the fat and fleſh of a <hi>Bear</hi> taken and kept cloſe in Troughs, or other convenient veſſels, do increaſe at the ſame time when as the Beares lying in their dens in the Winter time do wax fat? Or why
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109298:22"/>
doth a Womans milke agitate and prick in her breaſts at the ſame time when the child (being abſent) for want of it is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet? Why do the Peaſe ſowed in the New of the Moon in ſeverall places, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to the end of the Harveſt bloſſome, and yet never bear? And why alſo ſhould that diſeaſe be fatall to many thouſands that hath been mortall to one man? And that (as <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hiſtories report) an <hi>Aquula</hi> or water prepared only for the purpoſe, did ſignifie and preſent the condition of the Kings Sonnes <hi>Oliverius</hi> and <hi>Artus,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they were many miles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant?</p>
               <p>Or as ſome have beheld two muſicall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments ſo proportionated that the ſtrings, of the one ſhould ſenſibly move with the ſound of the other, and non to ſtir at the ſound of any other inſtrument? What ſhould be the reaſon that bloud ſhould guſh forth from the body of one ſlain, when the Homicide is in preſence, and as it were point him out? Or that the <hi>Ellychnium</hi> or match of a Lampe fired by a ſingular Artifice ſhould certainly predict the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe and death of the perſon (though far diſtant) whoſe bloud is adhibited or applied unto it?</p>
               <p>I ſpeak not of the <hi>Magnetiſme</hi> of the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109298:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Electrum</hi> (or <hi>Amber</hi>) which though ſhut up in ſeverall boxes, hath the ſame virtue of transferring and conveying the ſecret inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the mind unto thoſe who are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and far remote: Nor of the <hi>Sambucum</hi> (or Elder) which hath the ſame, if not greater, virtue againſt the falling Evill, whoſe berries do increaſe and grow ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by the putrefyed bodies of dead Sparrowes and Magpies, and ſometimes by their excrements or dung: Alſo the root of <hi>Tamarisk</hi> ſteeped in the urine of one that hath the yellow Jaundiſe, and afterward burned in the fire, cureth the ſame. And the hearb <hi>Condyloma</hi> (or <hi>Mullein</hi>) applyed to the diſeaſed and caſt into the ayre, doth admirably cure the <hi>Haemorroids.</hi> And alſo that there is ſometimes a leſſer, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a contrary quality in Vegitives of the ſame ſpecies; which may likewiſe be ſaid of the diſpoſitions and natures of men, borne under either equall or different Aſcendants or Climats.</p>
               <p>The true cauſe of all which, is the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of <hi>ſpirituall Mumie</hi> under the certain ſtars or genius of every thing deſtined and impowered by <hi>ſacred providence,</hi> by whoſe excelling ſtrength and motions all ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate things enjoy in every part <hi>alale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall</hi> and true proportionall virtues, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109298:23"/>
ſome hindrance by accident (as by the impurity or inequality of the matter) do intervene.</p>
               <p>So that hence is the diverſity of things of the ſame ſpecies, according to a greater or leſſer power, for they may hinder all the Celeſtiall influences by the confuſion and inhability or impotency of their matter: Hence alſo ſpringeth that proverb of the <hi>Platoniſts,</hi> The heavenly influences operate ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the merit or goodneſſe of the matter, and thoſe things in which the <hi>Idea</hi> of the matter is moſt predominant (<hi>viz.</hi> which have a greater ſimilitude to the things ſeparated) can more properly operate the like virtues and effects as the ſeparated <hi>Idea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the very reaſon, and true Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicall cauſe of the <hi>ſympathy</hi> of things, to which all other (unleſſe made <hi>Appendices</hi> to this) that have been with much ſtudy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, and with great applauſe received, muſt neceſſarily give place.</p>
               <p>Heare what <hi>Scaliger</hi> ſayeth (a man of that accurate judgement that I ſhould ſcarce beleeve he could be deceived) <q>It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine (ſayeth he) that there are ſome things which are common to <hi>ſpecies,</hi> and therefore are inforced to a certaine Congruency; and ſo there are certaine
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109298:24"/>
diſtinct qualities or contrarieties of kinds, from whence proceeds different <hi>ſpecies;</hi> and theſe are the originall of <hi>Sympathies</hi> and <hi>Antipathies.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But if a genericall community be the adequate cauſe of <hi>ſympathy,</hi> how comes it to paſſe, that all ſpecies of what kinde ſoever, have without order the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruency amongſt themſelves? I ſpeak of the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>vocall genus,</hi> for all <hi>ſpecies</hi> have not equally one and the ſame affections: For example; ſuppoſe the <hi>ſpecies</hi> of the Equivocall <hi>genus</hi> were here to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; then the <hi>ſympatheticall</hi> Cancer would not be rightly an Animal, as other fiſhes, without that Sympathy: If alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congruent differences of <hi>Genus's,</hi> be the cauſe of Antipathy in <hi>Species,</hi> (which nevertheleſſe would be manifeſt <hi>(petitio principii)</hi> to affirm what he doth not in the interim tell in what the difference conſiſteth) how cometh it to paſſe, that all ſpecies of this difference are not <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patheticall?</hi> As for example; one Antipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theticall affection of a man being common to every <hi>individuall</hi> man, why (ſeeing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man equally participates of the form of difference) ſhould they not have princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples tending to thoſe contrary affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:109298:24"/>Therefore the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> ſeemeth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſedly to carp at the <hi>Phyſician,</hi> yea, by his favour, I may ſay) unjuſtly; for, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hough he endevours to refute <hi>Fracaſtorius,</hi> to whom, in this point, more credit is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e given) or makes at him as it were with ſeverall paſſes, yet they may eaſily be put by, or avoyded, if we ſhall underſtand by the conjunction of <hi>form</hi> in <hi>Sympatheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cals</hi> and their propagation (which <hi>Scaliger</hi> doth chiefly oppoſe) not the <hi>form</hi> as it is diſtinguiſhed from the whole <hi>matter</hi> and ſubſtance, but the <hi>ſpecies</hi> out of them ſpringing and ariſing together: and by the conjunction no other thing then the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion and mutuall application of the power and properties of it, by which it operates.</p>
               <p>The effuſion or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (emanation) of theſe and the like properties we ſhall here deliver.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> affirmeth, that the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or extraction and tranſplantation of <hi>Mumie,</hi> may be made, and effected without the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution of the thing, or the ſubſtantiall form of it; therefore it muſt be an <hi>Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens</hi> which muſt be ſubſtracted, and which is uſed as the means of tranſplantation, and that properly; its <hi>eſſence</hi> being not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether divided from the ſubſtance of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109298:25"/>
thing, which with the ſpirit of the matter being brought to its extremeſt bounds, immediately with the property of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Microcoſmicall <hi>Magnetiſme,</hi> by a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall concurrency is united; and laſtly, by the mediation of the Terrene ſtars, and the Celeſtiall Spirits and Influences i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> accommodated, and by their adſpiration and conjunction, through a certain occult virtue of their Conſtitutions it gaineth ſo much as before it wanted of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, <hi>Tranſplantion</hi> is nothing elſe but a mutuall propagation of one thing into another, by the benefit of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of Eſſentiall <hi>Mumie</hi> duely extracted by a <hi>Magneticall</hi> virtue; and thence by their equall cognation with the ſtars, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted to a ſingular excellency and forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</p>
               <p>(The difference of <hi>Mumie</hi> followeth.)</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:109298:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the differences of <hi>Mumie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WEE ſhall not here inquire after the differences of <hi>Mumie</hi> in generall, for that hath been principally treated of in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>recedent Chapter, but onely of thoſe which fall out in the Caſes of <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> which hee calleth <hi>Corporeall:</hi> Theſe are to be taken from the nature of the Elements, to which the bodies after death are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed; for as they by themſelves have not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> like operations, but interchangeably diſcede from themſelves with great difference; as in the <hi>fire,</hi> their fiery; in the <hi>air,</hi> their airy qualities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhewing proprieties that are ſometimes very contrary among themſelves; ſo the generations and corruptions of things begun in the ſame and perfected, are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by an extreme difference from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; nor are the conditions of generated and corrupted things every where the ſame; For example, in generated things the airy fleſh of Birds is not the ſame with the watery fleſh of Fiſhes, nor the fiery fleſh of the Wolf and Lyon the ſame with the earthy fleſh of the Oxe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:109298:26"/>So bodies receive a nature, clearly diſtinct from the diverſe Elements to which after death they are committed: for when a <hi>humane</hi> body is left by death in the bowels of the earth, then it endureth an earthy &amp; a kind of tepid putrefaction, the ſpirit within being ſuffocated, ſo that its <hi>Mumie</hi> is loathſome and not proper for uſe. So likewiſe a body in <hi>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> followeth the nature of the Element, and turneth into a <hi>mucilaginous</hi> or ſlimy kinde of putrefaction, which is alſo pernicious to the vitall ſpirit or <hi>Mumie</hi> of a thing. The <hi>fire</hi> is altogether deſtructive both to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and body, ſo that it wholly demoliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it, and driveth out the <hi>Mumie</hi> whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, unleſſe its certain degree or quantity be obſerved.</p>
               <p>Wherefore there are four <hi>corporeall Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> ſpecified by <hi>Paracelſus (viz.)</hi> of the Fire, Water, Earth, and Aire, but the three for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer doe (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) as it were <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuperficially</hi> and <hi>uncommodiouſly</hi> make up thoſe kindes of <hi>Mumie,</hi> only that <hi>Mumie</hi> of the Aire remaineth uſefull; and that is ſo far from being in the leaſt degree apt for the conſervation of <hi>humane</hi> life, that it is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther quite contrary, (to wit) more tending to <hi>antipathy</hi> then <hi>ſympathy,</hi> and more ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall (although forbidden by the Divine Law) then beneficiall. There are princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:109298:26"/>
two cauſes of this; Firſt the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the whole body putrefying within it ſelf; by which the Earth and water of the <hi>Microcoſme,</hi> are forced to return into their firſt <hi>macrocoſmicall ens;</hi> and ſeeing the other two Elements (<hi>viz.</hi> Aire and Fire) are the retinacle and ſtay of life, which on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſſeſſe a perfect and incorrupted body, therefore that preſently ſeparates from the other three <hi>Mumies</hi> aforementioned, and retires into the living body of the <hi>Macro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſmicall Element,</hi> which receiveth it even as the field doth the eſſence of the dung: we do require nothing from <hi>Mumies</hi> for the preſervation of <hi>humane</hi> life, but the very <hi>life</hi> (which conſiſteth in the <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>aire,</hi> or more properly) is defined to be Calor and <hi>Spirit</hi> entire, therefore they retain nothing more in themſelves that may be uſefull for extraction.</p>
               <p>The other cauſe is the ſame with the former concerning the elemented parts returning to the Elements; this only excepted, that it is to be taken out of thoſe bodies that periſh by the violence of the other three Elements: But here we ſhall only ſpeak (and that properly) of thoſe that dye by defect of body, or neceſſity of diſeaſes; for this in reſpect of its decaying virtue, is not to be preferred before the other three (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected)
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:109298:27"/>
                  <hi>Mumies;</hi> for although they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> diſſolved by the ſenſible action of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Elements, yet they internally co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rupt them in an inſenſible and indiſcern manner; which afterward cauſeth not o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a diſſenſion, but alſo an inteſtine conten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on to the utter ruine, deſtruction, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolution of themſelves in ſeverall m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners according to their degrees of pred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minancy: Whence proceedeth the vario<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Idea</hi> of diſeaſes, ſometimes the <hi>Drop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> from the pluviall impetuoſity of Wate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſometimes the <hi>Feaver</hi> from the Nitro-ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phurous predominancy of Fire; otherwh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Leproſie</hi> from the impreſſion of Eart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and many more which the Phyſitians o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mention in their <hi>Pathologicall</hi> Treatiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore this corruption of Elemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> being quickly moved, the <hi>Mumiall</hi> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſame of life, and vitall ſpirit (their hab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tation being diſſipated) muſt of neceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ceaſe; and <hi>transfixed</hi> bodies being af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> this manner ſeiſed on, or ſurpriſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſudden death, have an unwholſome a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> unprofitable <hi>Mumie,</hi> improper for uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> calleth in the Germa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tongue, <hi>Die Mumien der am Schelmen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſtorbenen Leíber,</hi> the Mumie of execute bodies.</p>
               <p>Which evils may be excited in theſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:109298:27"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mies contrarily and Antipathetically ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rding to the imprinted infection of every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ody, which we may gather from thoſe that we eaten the boild fleſh of a mad Wolfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Dog, who preſently become mad them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lves; alſo the boyled liquor of peſtilentiall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>kaſſes, being ſprinkled upon poſts, handles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f doors, &amp;c. do cauſe a moſt peſtilentiall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fection; whereof there are divers ſorts; that which proceeds from the Mumie of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orcereſſes, from the duſt of infected Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ires, and from the Mumie which draweth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> infection from <hi>Spermate</hi> diabolicall ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, &amp;c. <hi>Theophr. Paracelſ.</hi> in his <hi>Tract.</hi> 2. <hi>de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtilitate,</hi> doth (upon good conſiderations) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ut obſcurely handle this Peſtilentiall infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion; wherefore ſeeing <hi>Paracelſus</hi> was ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng herein, we ſhall modeſtly forbear to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eat of it, leſt we ſhould enduce any one too prone of themſelves) to practiſe ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpieties.</p>
               <p>But to the matter; a body dying by the interception of <hi>aire,</hi> receiving not tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all or forcible impreſſion Elementary into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s corporall Maſſe, remaineth wholly unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>troyed, and is leſſe ſubject to the Elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ary reſolution or putrefaction, ſo long as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t is preſerved and kept under a moiſt <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and in the <hi>Aire:</hi> And that becauſe the evolation of the watry humour being acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:109298:28"/>
by the <hi>aire</hi> and <hi>motion,</hi> doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the oily and Balſamick humor in their Eſſence, which would otherwiſe be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyed with the watery humour; And this plainly appears by wood burned in the fire (which we vulgarly call Charcoal) and in fleſh ſmoaked (in the chimney or otherwiſe) by which means they are more durable, and alſo retain their alible and nutrimentall juice entire; from whence they are uſually had in great requeſt.</p>
               <p>Thus it happeneth that the <hi>Mumiall</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits ſuffering extremely by the preſent evill, are drawn and retired into their chiefeſt (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) ripeneſſe and perfection, and are powerfully, and exactly commiſcera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with their moſt internall ſubſtances; as a living body is more capable of any faculties, ſo after death being indued with this <hi>Balſamick</hi> potency more internally, more powerfully reſiſteth the putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying habitude of the Elements, and defendeth it ſelf againſt all encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of adulterating corruption. For the clearing of which there are diverſe arguments; (for inſtance) bodies diſſected into many parts (though they have not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall ſpirits, but incluſed) do contrary to their nature leap and ſtirre up and down with ſeverall motions; inſomuch that they
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:109298:28"/>
are vulgarly eſteemed innocent and not able to die while the ſun is above the <hi>Horizon:</hi> And ſometimes a dog is obſerved to bark (as it were) and make many motions, his heart being cut out, as if he would tell <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> he was deceived in his opinion, when he ſaid <hi>the heart is the firſt that liveth, and the laſt that dyeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, the <hi>Balſame</hi> is not neceſſitated to depart from the body or habitation of the ſpirit, or vitall <hi>Balſame,</hi> ſo long as it remaineth entire and unhurt, in what part ſoever it is ſo irreſoluted or reſolved into its <hi>Elements;</hi> and therefore nothing is here dere linquiſhed or ſeparated but the anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting rationall <hi>ſoul,</hi> or the informing form of man, whoſe preſence gave a difference to every thing ſpecifically; for a man being defunct and reduced into <hi>Mumie,</hi> is no more a man but equivocally; and the vitall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, vegetable, naturall <hi>Balſame,</hi> the <hi>Symphyſis,</hi> and with it the exuberancy of the occult powers, in ſuch a body ſuffer no damage.</p>
               <p>Therefore the <hi>Aereall Mumie</hi> only of the <hi>Microcoſme,</hi> being extracted and ſeparated for the preſervation of the health of man, (and for many other uſes hereafter ſpecified) is approved of; ſo that the perſon or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject during life was perfectly healthfull and found, without any troubleſome paſſion,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:109298:29"/>
or eſſentiall conſtitution of parts or offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding faculty, which may occaſion any <hi>Mumiall</hi> imperfection, for thoſe procure an Antipatheticall operation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Extraction of <hi>Aereall Mumie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PAracelſus</hi> in many places wonderfully extolleth and openly profeſſeth that the <hi>Balſame</hi> of the <hi>Aereall Mumie</hi> of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crocoſme</hi> doth preſerve the health of mans body, becauſe it moſt powerfully reſiſteth all ſorts of poyſons received; it expelleth the contagious intoxication of the plague, and many other diſeaſes: And that (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) the efficacy and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, in perfection of <hi>Aurum potabile,</hi> and of all other things of the greater world, even of the Philoſophers Stone, may be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and raiſed from it: wherefore I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it requiſite to unfold this <hi>myſtery</hi> more deliberately, and more accurately to ſet down the Extraction of it: In the purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance whereof I finde that this <hi>Aereall Mumie</hi> may be ſeparated &amp; extracted ſeveral waies; as following.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:109298:29"/>Firſt, it is performed by the way of <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaction</hi> and <hi>ſeparation</hi> of <hi>Elements,</hi> and their <hi>combination,</hi> ſo that from thence ariſeth a new body in reſpect of the difference in its members, the <hi>Mumie</hi> being extracted hence retaineth all its former properties whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, and is moſt ready to aſſiſt them in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the Extraction of <hi>Mumie</hi> is perfected after the manner of <hi>Quinteſſence,</hi> of which in our firſt <hi>Tract, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, by the deſtruction of the Body, and afterward tranſplanting the ſpirit of the <hi>Mumie</hi> into another vegetable body.</p>
               <p>Take theſe three <hi>Extractions</hi> particularly handled for their better explication and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in the Tractates following.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:109298:30"/>
                  <head>The firſt manner of Extraction of <hi>Mumie: Or,</hi> Of the Tincture of the <hi>Microcoſme.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>COrporeall Mumie</hi> is to be taken when as the ſubſtance adhering to every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the <hi>liver, lungs,</hi> or the <hi>whole body,</hi> (by which is underſtood the <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>bloud</hi>) do putrefie during the time of a <hi>Philoſophicall moneth</hi> in a viall <hi>Hermetically</hi> cloſed, that it may have (as it were) a <hi>mucilaginous</hi> form: the <hi>Muccago</hi> or <hi>filthy matter</hi> being wrung or drained from it, muſt be laid in dung to putrefie a <hi>Philoſophicall moneth,</hi> that ſo it may be reduced into a <hi>Spagiricall Embryon;</hi> let the water be ſeparated from this <hi>Embryon matter</hi> in <hi>Balneo Mariae,</hi> and the <hi>aire</hi> in <hi>Aſhes;</hi> The water being again powred on the reſidue, and the <hi>ſignature</hi> duly interpoſited, let it pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefie another moneth in <hi>Balneo Mariae;</hi> then muſt the Water and Fire being extracted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by Aſhes, the Water being ſeparated from the Fire through <hi>Balneo Mariae,</hi> and rectifying the Fire apart by Aſhes: This will ſo ſeparate the <hi>Elements</hi> (though the aforeſaid <hi>Embryonian Earth</hi> may yet require another purgation) as if they were reſolved into their three <hi>principles.</hi> After which let
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:109298:30"/>
that <hi>Foeculent</hi> and droſſie Earth be <hi>reverbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated</hi> or boiled in a cloſe veſſell for four daies; then let the Element of Water be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled by a <hi>Balneall temper,</hi> that it may only conſume the <hi>heterogeneous humidity;</hi> the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due is to be perfected by Aſhes.</p>
                  <p>The water that floweth upon the <hi>rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berated</hi> Earth boyling in Aſhes, muſt three or four times by a ſtrong fire be repelled and forced out, ſo ſhall it appear more <hi>pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucide</hi> and clear, and will be <hi>rectified</hi> with the proper Earth by the ſame work.</p>
                  <p>In like manner perfect the Aire upon the Earth by <hi>cohobating</hi> it to a <hi>purity</hi> and reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable <hi>ſapor.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then proceeding to the Fire; let that mixed with the Water, be put into a place fit for putrefaction for ſome few daies, ſo ſhal the <hi>Empyreuma</hi> (or droſſe of the Fire) be abſtracted from the water by an <hi>Arenari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> or ſandy kind of diſtillation; then ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate again the Water from thence in <hi>Balneo Mariae,</hi> afterward place it to putrefie for ſome three daies mixed with the Earth; then diſtill it by the Sand in a ſtrong fire, and the fire will riſe up together with the Sand, which is to be ſeparated from the Water, the fire remaining in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome.</p>
                  <p>Purſue the ſame <hi>Infuſion, Distillation,</hi> and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:109298:31"/>
                     <hi>Separation</hi> from this Element of the Earth, untill nothing of that Fire remain in the bottome; the Water at length being ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated (after it hath been divided from the clear Fire remaining three dayes) muſt be <hi>abſtracted</hi> from it throughly by <hi>Balneo Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae;</hi> the Fire at laſt being reduced to the Calor of Aſhes; this will ſublimate this laborious <hi>rectification</hi> being of a more weakly <hi>operation:</hi> For thus by <hi>cohoba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> the Airy <hi>Balſame</hi> from the Water and Aire, will be <hi>conciliated</hi> to the Fire, and the Fiery <hi>Balſame</hi> by Fire to the Water; ſo that the laſt Liquors will be reſpondent to the two firſt Principles, <hi>Mercury</hi> and <hi>Sulphur;</hi> which afterward being rectified by a <hi>circular</hi> motion will return into their proper Center, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the <hi>Mercuriall Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor</hi> with the <hi>Sal,</hi> but the <hi>Sulphur</hi> cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culating by its ſelf will paſſe into its own Center.</p>
                  <p>The third <hi>Principle</hi> muſt be perfected according to the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> or operation fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>reverberated</hi> Earth bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten upon Marble muſt be ſteeped in four times as much of the Water ſeparated in the firſt diſtillation by the <hi>Balneo,</hi> and muſt again be <hi>coagulated</hi> by Aſhes, and ſo to be continued untill the Earth ſhall have throughly ſucked up the Fire, (for it will
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:109298:31"/>
be <hi>ſublimated</hi> to the likeneſſe of Snow) ſo the more impure part, as the Tares ſowed in the field of Nature, hindering the juncture of familiarity and concord, ſhall be wholly relinquiſhed and left re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected.</p>
                  <p>Which earth being refined by <hi>ſublimation,</hi> will truely make the third <hi>principle (viz.) Sol,</hi> which is the <hi>Mater</hi> into which the other two <hi>(Mercury</hi> and <hi>Sulphur)</hi> are to be perfectly received as the procreating <hi>Spermate</hi> of Man and Woman, being appointed and approved for a new and admirable increaſe, containing in it ſelf the <hi>Portracture</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> of the whole World: (I mean of the <hi>Tincture</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted out of the <hi>Microcoſme</hi>) and therefore called by the name of the <hi>Microcoſme</hi> or <hi>little World,</hi> but rather by the title of the <hi>Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſmicall ſtone of Philoſophers,</hi> ſeeing it a <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine</hi> for all diſeaſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <gap reason="missing" resp="#UOM" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:109298:32"/>
                  <head>The third manner of Extraction, or of <hi>Aereall Mumie.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Third Extraction is of <hi>Aereall Mumie</hi> or of the Balſame of the body <hi>prefocated</hi> and this muſt be done by the means of <hi>Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, let the <hi>Mumie</hi> being mixed in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> fourth part of hot and dry earth be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in a cloſe veſſell for a month, or untill i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hath a <hi>mucilaginous</hi> form, then put in the ſeeds of ſuch plants whoſe virtues are effectuall againſt the diſeaſes you would have cured, <hi>viz.</hi> for the Plague <hi>Antipeſtilentiall ſeeds;</hi> for Feavers the ſeeds of Plants contrary to them, and ſo of the reſt; ſo leave them in the open ayre while they begin to ſprout and grow; for the <hi>magneticall</hi> virtue of the ſeed and its <hi>ſpirit</hi> ſwelling in it, doth not only anſwer in proportion of Ayre, but the ſame (although often changing its <hi>nature</hi> with the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of it) doeth as it were nouriſh the inward <hi>Balſamick ſpirit</hi> of the <hi>Mumiall Earth,</hi> and ſo while it thus vegetates it will aſſociate the <hi>ſpirituall</hi> virtues and properties of that ſame <hi>Mumie</hi> with it ſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:109298:32"/>Moreover, the Extraction of the ſame <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>arbe</hi> skilfully mediated with the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne, after the manner of the <hi>Quinteſſence</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d <hi>Magisterium,</hi> will be very commodious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d uſefull for the conſervation of health, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d repelling of many diſeaſes. Which <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ſtery</hi> of <hi>Tranſplantation</hi> is more amply <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>dled in the ſubſequent Chapter; And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ugh many reaſons may be given for <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>all Extractions,</hi> yet I ſhall only here lay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wn Three as moſt principall and requiſite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhew the potency and operation of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ore ſecret <hi>Medicine;</hi> the reſt (through the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>rt</hi> and <hi>Alembick</hi>) I will leave to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rofeſſor.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:109298:33"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Of the</hi> Spirituall Mumie <hi>of a</hi> Micr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>coſmicall <hi>living body.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THeophraſtus Parac.</hi> (in his Book <hi>de T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pore</hi>) having finiſhed the four ſorts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Corporeall Mumie,</hi> as in the former Series; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcendeth now to a more myſticall and adm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable <hi>Mumie</hi> as he expreſſeth in theſe word <hi>Quod inſuper alid Mumia deture vivo exiſten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> corpore, vel exquavis ejus parte, integris &amp; inoffenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> iis permanentibus, extrabenda, &amp;c.</hi> There m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be alſo another <hi>Mumie</hi> extracted from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>living</hi> body, or from any member or pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thereof remaining whole and entire, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> will cure many affections (otherwiſe inc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable) by a common and eaſie way, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which, as by a naturall and wholeſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Philtre,</hi> a loving and mutuall complacenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is procured between a man incenſed again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his wife; and many other excellent <hi>expe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riments</hi> are found in it, though ſome ig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>norant and evill diſpoſed people will no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> grant any ſuch thing in nature; who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> frivolous arguments and ſophiſtry bette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> experience hath conſuted. Theſe (Expe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riments) have hitherto been much con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cealed
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:109298:33"/>
from the moſt <hi>learned,</hi> and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tanding have been uſed by the <hi>Ruſticall</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mon people,</hi> of whom ſome by this <hi>Mumie</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ve cauſed their Heards, Geeſe, Hens, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>geons to love them, others have (with like ſucceſſe) given it to Dogges, Falcons, Stags, and Lyons, by which they have been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, and alſo by the proper uſe of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y have perſwaded and allured wilde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſts into their nets; which <hi>myſtery</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>Magnetiſme</hi> I intend not in this place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ther to enlarge.</p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Paracelſus</hi> (in <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de Origine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b. inviſib.</hi> toward the end) ſpeaketh thus, which for the benefit of the matter and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elegancy of the ſtile, I have here recited in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is own Language.) <hi>Ran die Sondurch em <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>laſs ſchetnen, unnd das Fewr durch den <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>en geben, unnd beyder Leib bleibet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>auſſen: So can auch der Leih ſeine Krafft <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n die Weite geben laſſen, unnd ſtill liegen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſſ wohl als die Sonn durch dz Glaſs, und <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ompt doch ſelbſt nicht dadurch: Drumb <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ird dem Leibe an ſich ſelbſt nichts zuge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſſen, ſondern den kraffte die anſs ihm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ben, ingleicher Weiſe, wie der Geſchmack <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on eim Biſem, deſs Leib auch ſtill lieget. Alſo find auff den Grund die Bielfeltigen <hi>Experimenten in Mumia</hi> erfunden worden, daſs man ſagt das Lheil am Menſchen iſt gut
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:109298:34"/>
dazu, das ander iſt gut zu den Dingen, dabon ich bie nicht ſchreiben wil, biſſ ich zerlege die <hi>Mumien</hi> in der Himmiſchen Schuel, in welchen Orten erklaret werden die Ding, ſo euch hie werden gebreſten, denn fie haben ſo groſſe Myſteria in ihnen, daſs fie eines trefflichen Buchs wel bedurffen, &amp;c.</hi> (which is thus rendred) If the Sun can ſhine through the Glaſſe, and the fire ſhine through the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, and the bodies of each is not neer, then the body alſo can ejaculate its virtue though it lyeth ſtill and comes no neerer then the Sun doth to the Glaſſe, for it doth not paſſe through the Glaſſe: And conſequently nothing is attributed to the body but to the virtues proceeding from it, even as the ſent which the Moſſe affords, whoſe body lyeth and ſtirreth not. The like Experiments were found in the <hi>Mumie</hi> upon good grounds, whereby it was known that ſome part of man was good for ſuch a thing, and ſome were found to do good otherwiſe; of which I intend not to write now, but refer it to the Schooles, when <hi>Mumie</hi> ſhall be <hi>Anatomized</hi> in a heavenly manner, where ſuch things ſhall be further declared, which you now ſtand in need of; for there are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained therein <hi>extraordinary Myſteries,</hi> whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration would require a great Volum.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:109298:34"/>Which words of <hi>Parucelſus</hi> do excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently deſcribe that <hi>Spirituall Mumie,</hi> and other <hi>Sympatheticall</hi> and <hi>Antipatheticall</hi> My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries.</p>
               <p>He demonſtrateth the true foundation and uſe of the <hi>Mumie</hi> (according to its do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine) under the example or type of the <hi>Magnet</hi> and <hi>Iron,</hi> by which virtue the <hi>Magnet</hi> doth alliciate the <hi>Iron</hi> unto it, ſhewing by it the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or true extraction of <hi>Spirituall Mumie</hi> and its hidden faculties (of which further hereafter, though he doth ſomewhat obliquely and obſcurely expreſſe himſelfe) by handling the thing it ſelf, and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof in theſe words, <hi>Spiritum Mumiae nullius uſus eſſe, niſi mediante vivo quoclam cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore;</hi> that the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>Mumie</hi> is of no uſe unleſſe to a living body: which ſome may ſeem to enforce from the 29. <hi>Pſal. For what profit is there in my bloud, when I deſcend into Corruption?</hi> Although many may ſuppoſe little or nothing is here meant of <hi>Spirituall Mumie,</hi> yet if any one will narrowly ſearch into it, by comparing truth with truth, he may (by a more diligent enquiry) finde out the true concordancy of the <hi>Magnet</hi> and <hi>Iron,</hi> with their properties, nature, originall and virtues: After which he will eaſily know how to apply the (mentioned) Example to the preſent purpoſe, and alſo
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:109298:35"/>
formes of different <hi>ſpecies</hi> are received in one and the ſame ſubject: We have an Example of this in the <hi>Lithopaedio Alboſii,</hi> and alſo in <hi>Coralls, Metalls,</hi> and in diverſe <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls,</hi> bearing the figures and likeneſſe of hearbs and other things: Now each forme <hi>(viz.)</hi> the <hi>Spirit</hi> or <hi>Theamedall</hi> forme by reaſon of its <hi>Lapidary Murcury,</hi> and the <hi>Martiall Spirit</hi> by reaſon of its <hi>Martiall Mercury,</hi> (in ſome meaſure) is received into the ſociety of the <hi>Lapidary Mercury,</hi> to which the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of the <hi>Celeſtiall motions</hi> particularly qualified is a faithfull and impart all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductor and coadjutor; for the ſubſtances, formes, and innate powers of the <hi>Terrene exiſtences</hi> depend on the <hi>aſſimilative aſpect</hi> of the heavens; and therefore they both are mutually inſpired by the <hi>Celeſtiall influences,</hi> and <hi>corrivally</hi> received into the love and boſome of the aforeſaid <hi>matter.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Arte poli vincliſque nova ratione paratis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thus heavens conſpiring, <hi>Art</hi> doth prove</l>
                  <l>A new found way to fetter <hi>Love.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>When as the <hi>Twin-husbands</hi> having happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly celebrated their <hi>Nuptialls,</hi> (with their aforeſaid <hi>Spouſes</hi>) by the <hi>conſummation</hi> of this Marriage, the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or more predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant <hi>Sulphurous Martiall Spirit</hi> endued with
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:109298:35"/>
a wonderfull mobility, ſubdueth and more internally poſſeſſeth the whole <hi>Mercuriall Lapidary liquor,</hi> the <hi>Metall</hi> merely proper be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abſent, &amp; the <hi>Theamedall ſpirit</hi> but weakly reſiſting and impotently endeavoring the performance of the ſame duty: On the other ſide the <hi>Lapidary Mercury</hi> by its cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation or affinity with the incloſed par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the <hi>Martiall Murcury,</hi> doth not only affectionately retain the <hi>Lapidary Spirit,</hi> but alſo the <hi>Martiall,</hi> and coagmenteth the <hi>Metall</hi> into a <hi>Lapidary body,</hi> by the mediation of the <hi>Sal;</hi> for the greater part of <hi>Mercury</hi> is <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidary,</hi> the leſſe <hi>Metallick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the whole <hi>Concrete</hi> is not alike, neither <hi>Iron</hi> nor <hi>Stone,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Herma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hroditicall</hi> or <hi>mixture</hi> of both, but yet, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in ſuch proportion, that the <hi>Lapidary Mercury</hi> may obtain its naturall matter from the <hi>Lapis,</hi> and its <hi>ſpirits</hi> from the <hi>Iron,</hi> the reſt being permanent &amp; exiſtent in it in the ſame quality, but in a leſſe quantity and efficacy.</p>
               <p>This is the Hiſtory of the <hi>Naturall Magne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick generation,</hi> from whence are the very principles and reaſons of all its proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; For in that it attracteth <hi>Iron,</hi> or is attracted to it in reſpect of its more maſſy (and ponderous) body, is becauſe the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurous Martiall Spirit</hi> being of a moveable and noble nature is intricated in an improper
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:109298:36"/>
the more powerfull one faculty is, the weaker is the other; and contrarily one of the <hi>Contraries</hi> being ſetled, the other is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, whence is its Converſion to the North? briefly hence; The <hi>heaven</hi> in that part of it, the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſae cauda</hi> (vulgarly called the Tail of the leſſer Bear, or any other Starre) is the <hi>principium</hi> of this particular nature in the <hi>Magnet,</hi> comprehending the reaſon of its whole being, as the <hi>Moon</hi> of the <hi>Selenite ſtone,</hi> the <hi>Sun</hi> of the <hi>Lothes,</hi> and other <hi>Heliotropiums;</hi> or in a certain ſenſe the <hi>Sea</hi> is the cauſe of all other waters; therefore the <hi>Celeſtiall Spirits</hi> flowing into the Rudiments, Complements, and Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this <hi>Creature</hi> more abundantly by reaſon of the immobility of the <hi>Polary ſtars,</hi> of which alſo the contrariety of the mobible <hi>Aire</hi> being a cauſe, is of ſuch nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble concernment, that they continually have the ſame motion of the <hi>Starre</hi> about the Earth; (which if you deſire a more nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row inſpection, it is ſufficiently experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in the <hi>Tract</hi> of the <hi>Loadſtone</hi>) and ſo that in whatſoever adverſity or exigence they are, they naturally deſire to eſcape and recreate themſelves this way, by which there is a conjunction with the familiar ſymboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and chiefeſt <hi>Celeſtiall Spirits,</hi> and a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:109298:36"/>
and natural inclination with all other <hi>Elements</hi> and <hi>Elementaries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hitherto ſufficiently of the <hi>Magnet;</hi> where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rſt we muſt note (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ording to its progreſſion, that the <hi>Magneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>all Attraction</hi> proceedeth from the <hi>Sulphurous Martiall Spirit,</hi> and the <hi>Coeleſtiall influence</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lominant in it.</p>
               <p>Wherefore it will be neceſſary and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ient to the exalting and extracting of the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>burous ſpirit</hi> of the <hi>Microcoſme,</hi> to try it by a <hi>Microcoſmicall Magnet</hi> bearing affinity with the <hi>Martiall Magnet;</hi> as in the ſubſequent Chapter ſhall be more largely declared.</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:109298:37"/>with it; ſo the generation and <hi>Principia</hi> of the <hi>Microcoſmicall Magnet</hi> is to be ſought (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) in the Excrements of the Entrails aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>The familiar nutriment of our nature being ſingularly ingeſted, and reduced by the <hi>Arches</hi> into the <hi>Materia prima</hi> or firſt matter, that <hi>liquid</hi> and <hi>Mercuriall ſubſtance,</hi> (for whither elſe can they more commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly apply then to the ſaid <hi>Lapidary Mercury</hi>) For thoſe things which the <hi>ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurous ſpirit</hi> of the <hi>Microcoſme</hi> doth ſo much traverſe up and down, being liquid, doe cleave unto the embracements of the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour inteſtines, and aſſociateth with them though contrary to it ſelf, no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then as the forme doth with the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is at length deduced through the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Conjunction being made when as they ſhall draw the <hi>Magnetick</hi> powers and faculties of its <hi>Microcoſmicall ſulphur,</hi> even as the <hi>Lapidary Mercury</hi> did the Spirits of the <hi>Martiall,</hi> doth not only deſerve the name of <hi>Mercury</hi> by its <hi>Analogie</hi> with the <hi>Lapidary Magnet</hi> (ſo called) but may moſt worthily be termed the <hi>Microcoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall Magnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That this is truely ſo, appeareth by that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:109298:37"/>
the <hi>Microcoſmicall Mercury</hi> indued with the ſaid <hi>ſpirit,</hi> demonſtrateth that <hi>Magnetick</hi> nature, dignity, and uſe by many various and wonderfull wayes, which is conſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and clearly exemplifyed by that <hi>extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poraneous ſympatheticall <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguent</hi> which is not unknown to many, eſpecially to <hi>Military men;</hi> for it is generally eſteemed the moſt ready (Cure), the Inſtrument or Weapon only that made the Wound being duely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted with it, wonderfuly mitigateth, and alſo healeth the Ulcer or Wound: So in the very <hi>Magnes</hi> of the <hi>Microcoſme</hi> (being diverſly diſpoſed) ſometimes it ſtrangely ſtoppeth the violent ſolutions of the belly, and (amongſt which) ſometimes the <hi>Dyſenteria</hi> or <hi>Bloudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flux,</hi> which if it be <hi>Epidemicall</hi> it hath its deſcent from above, and ſometimes it great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly provokes them: And this is generally obſerved even by the common ſort of people the ſaid <hi>Magnet</hi> being burned or fired either by throwing burning Coales on it, or elſe by burnt Wine and pepper together, ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon it, doth with as much torment afflict the <hi>Nates depoſitoris inciviles,</hi> as the burning Coales themſelves, were they apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ſame parts.</p>
               <p>Of which ſaith <hi>Paracel. (in Tract.</hi> 1. <hi>de modo Pharmacandi:</hi>) that the aforeſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:109298:38"/>
                  <hi>ſpirit</hi> of Man, (according to their ſevera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>natures</hi> and <hi>proportion</hi>) draweth with as muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alacrity and aptneſſe, as is before ſpecifye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the <hi>Attractive faculty</hi> of the <hi>Loadſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to <hi>Iron, (viz.)</hi> from the well and ſoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> part a ſound and well diſpoſed <hi>Spir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> from the diſeaſed a languiſhing <hi>Spirit</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with that diſeaſe, as this Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive appetite is naturall to every thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> its like; and there is an eaſie ſolutio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the parts of a ſubject when as like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> drawn by power of its like; in which reſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that of <hi>Heraclitus</hi> is not abſurd, <hi>Omnia fieri p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> amicitiam &amp; per litem,</hi> all things are do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> by amity and ſtrife. Of which more amply<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in another place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:109298:38"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of the uſe of <hi>Spirituall Mumie</hi> (in generall.)</head>
               <p>IT is affirmed before from <hi>Theophraſtus,</hi> that the <hi>Spirituall Mumie</hi> extracted from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e propoſed <hi>Magnes,</hi> is of no uſe, neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n it effect any thing, unleſſe a live body or <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>getable Animal</hi> doth intercede, &amp; not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t reaſon, for ſeeing the <hi>virtue</hi> muſt only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſue out of the body, it would be more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpotent and uncapable of procuring effects worthy its <hi>originall;</hi> for nothing operates beyond its <hi>ſpecies</hi> and <hi>degree;</hi> therefore it muſt of neceſſity be inveſted with ſuch a ſubſtance, whoſe interiour <hi>Anatomy</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>harmony</hi> of the <hi>Heavens</hi> doth as much agree with it as its former ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from whence it was <hi>extracted,</hi> or whoſe condition is the ſame with the former in the <hi>ſeries</hi> of the <hi>Celeſtiall dignities;</hi> for it is moſt certaine and confirmed by invincible Experience, that theſe <hi>Terreſtriall</hi> things diſpoſe themſelves in order to theſe <hi>Celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,</hi> and that what happeneth to one by the virtue of the <hi>Celeſtials,</hi> that preſently by the concordancy of the <hi>ſuperiour</hi> (powers) is
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:109298:39"/>
unto it, and transferred into ſome vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſubject capable of the <hi>vitall power</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> increaſing it, might by its <hi>ſpirituall</hi> attractor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> virtue be continually augmented.</p>
               <p>To which may be anſwered, that al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>though the <hi>Magnes</hi> of the <hi>Microcoſme</hi> wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> extract ſome part of the <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> yet i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will not do it ſufficiently, nor ſo much a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is neceſſary for <hi>tranſplanting</hi> or <hi>eradicatin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> diſeaſes, but this tranſlation to anothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> body will make it leſſe <hi>operative,</hi> being ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhed from its own: Of which more at larg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the enſuing <hi>Proceſſion</hi> (being a continuatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of this <hi>Extraction.</hi>)</p>
               <p>Take <hi>Magnetick Earth,</hi> into which ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſpirituall Mumie</hi> being received by <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentation,</hi> let it be inſeminated into ſeed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or implanted into ſome hearbe prope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for the diſeaſe and member you woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cure; as</p>
               <p>For the
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jaundies</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dropſie</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pluriſie</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Plague</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers</hi> &amp;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Wounds</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
into
<list>
                     <item>Line-ſeed, Hemp-ſeed Juniperberies.</item>
                     <item>Pimpernel, Cammo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> Wormwood.</item>
                     <item>Saint-Johns-Wort,</item>
                     <item>Scordium, Plantane,</item>
                     <item>Spotted Arſmart.</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:109298:39"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d ſo in the reſt, by adhibiting their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r guides: Let them grow and vegetate in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e open <hi>Ayre,</hi> and ſo the <hi>Attractive</hi> proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y will wax much ſtronger, and through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>vegetative</hi> nature, will wholly draw and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ck up the <hi>Mumiall</hi> ſpirits, <hi>Sympathetically</hi> and <hi>Antipathetically,</hi> by the benefit of the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>it</hi> of the World; and through the means <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the <hi>ſeminall</hi> quality of its <hi>ſpecies,</hi> (if its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>roper <hi>form</hi> ſhould degenerate) it will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>in and keep its properties without any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ifficulty: And this proceeds from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ongruity of <hi>forms</hi> in both; namely, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e member adminiſtring <hi>Spirituall Mumie,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd in the <hi>ſeed</hi> or <hi>plants</hi> conforming to it; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herefore, if the infected member be weak, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e impotency thereof will be transferred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>ſeed</hi> or <hi>plant;</hi> if it bee naturally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ong, they will alſo, after their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, participate: And this is readily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cted by the meanes aforeſaid, as a kinde of <hi>Magicall</hi> allurement and preparative, which is apt to receive the <hi>Celeſtiall</hi> infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions.</p>
               <p>But it is to be obſerved, that the <hi>plants</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r <hi>fruit</hi> muſt be diverſly ordered (that they may the more eaſily work this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect) and accommodated to the <hi>nature</hi> and ſeverall conditions of the <hi>Diſeaſe:</hi> As for Example.</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:109298:40"/>of the <hi>vitall</hi> World, through the <hi>Rayes</hi> of the Stars opportunely applyed. (But to our purpoſe.)</p>
               <p>It is now carefully to be looked unto, that the hearb or tree with which the <hi>Mumie</hi> out of the ſound member is mixed, may not decay or be cut, but that with all care it may be preſerved alive and growing; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that vegetable <hi>ſpecies</hi> muſt be tranſplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the very <hi>kernell,</hi> neer the root of a ſhady and green tree, the hole being firmly cloſed up again, that ſo the <hi>moyſture</hi> of it may more properly be exhauſted, and by apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every thing rightly, the operation may the more effectually ſucceed</p>
               <p>And it muſt alſo as carefully be obſerved, that the <hi>fruit</hi> or <hi>tree</hi> into which the diſeaſe is <hi>tranſplanted,</hi> do not grow up too <hi>ſuddenly</hi> and <hi>rankly,</hi> (which often happens) for ſuch <hi>ſuperfluous vegetation</hi> is dangerous, and hurtful for the member: This may appear by the example of <hi>Hair,</hi> which is often <hi>tranſplanted</hi> into a <hi>Willow,</hi> that it may grow the faſter, nor is it without ſucceſſe; but when they are left in it beyond their proper time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not cut down nor burned, that over rank and moiſt <hi>vegetation</hi> oftentimes proveth hurtfull to the <hi>brain</hi> and <hi>eyes,</hi> eſpecially to the latter; which is alſo dangerous to any afflicted or troubled with <hi>Phthiſick</hi> and <hi>Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:109298:40"/>
(while they happily think themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ure;) which onely proceeds from this er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, that they improvidently place their <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nies</hi> in <hi>herbs</hi> and <hi>trees</hi> of a <hi>rank</hi> or too <hi>quick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo, you muſt carefully provide, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> chooſe a <hi>ſpecies</hi> temperated according to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e condition of the <hi>perſon</hi> or member in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſted, that ſo it may rightly perform its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ty.</p>
               <p>Which proportion of generall <hi>harmony</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>very commendable: As for example, the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ake</hi> eminent for its <hi>duration,</hi> and of a <hi>ſlow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>th,</hi> is therefore moſt proper for the <hi>teeth</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Children (ſhedding them the firſt ſeaven <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ears) to be <hi>tranſplanted</hi> into, to avert any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſeaſes from them, during their whole life. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or with leſſe reaſon againſt the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſtenneſſe</hi> of Children, a wedged piece of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cke</hi> is taken, with a certain quantity of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arley corns,</hi> upon which cauſe the Childe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o make water for ſome few dayes, then dig from under the <hi>Oake</hi> a handfull of <hi>freſh Earth,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd mingle it with the <hi>Barley;</hi> after which, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it a <hi>young Oak,</hi> and put the <hi>Earth</hi> mixt with the <hi>Barley</hi> together into it, and alſo the aforeſaid <hi>wedge</hi> of <hi>Oak,</hi> not without a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall <hi>Mumiall</hi> reaſon, like this of ours; which may likewiſe occaſion the commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ations of that <hi>Shrub,</hi> which is ſaid to be
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:109298:41"/>
from Antiquity, (namely) a <hi>Bath</hi> made o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the blood of <hi>Infants,</hi> for curing the <hi>Leproſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and to reſtore corrupted fleſh: So that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (without cauſe of injury) hath rendre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> certain Kings hatefull to the Common peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple.</p>
               <p>For it is both deteſtable, improfitable and noxious, in reſpect of <hi>nutrition,</hi> to receive the parts themſelves, and <hi>humane</hi> blood into the body; for, <hi>illud quod nutrit, non plane corpori debet eſſe homogeneum,</hi> that which nouriſheth ought not properly to be <hi>homogoneall</hi> with the body; becauſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a like thing cauſeth evill effects; an example whereof we have in <hi>Faustina</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Emperour <hi>Antonius,</hi> who drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the blood of a <hi>Gladiator,</hi> whom ſhe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, it wrought, in ſtead of love, a ſtrange hatred, (as <hi>Julius Capitilonus</hi> writeth:) And that <hi>Roman</hi> (of whom <hi>Schrammius</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in <hi>Faſciculo Hiſtoriarum</hi>) who drinking the blood which guſhed out of his owne vein, wonderfully forgot that <hi>Learning</hi> which before he was exquiſite in: I might alſo inſtance the blood of a Cat, which ſometimes having been drunk, did infuſe a ſtrange madneſſe, with a Cats geſture and yawling. Many other examples might be produced of this nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:109298:41"/>Therefore, if it be required to give <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> extracted from another, to any man, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>feſt way is to preſcribe the whole <hi>fruit</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reaſed by that <hi>tranſplantation</hi> to be eaten or drunk; or otherwiſe, give the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of it extracted by the benefit of the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of Wine; both which will be ſucceſſefull: Whereof more at large in the Tract of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Amity</hi> following.</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:109298:42"/>muſt be eſteemed the firſt <hi>Cauſe;</hi> whence i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the firſt and principle <hi>motion</hi> of all things And (<hi>in lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Generatione</hi>) he ſaith that the <hi>Heavens</hi> was accompted by the an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cient <hi>Philoſophers</hi>) for the <hi>Progenitor,</hi> or fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Parent:</p>
               <p>Nor doth ſubtle <hi>Scaliger (in Exere.</hi> 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Subtil. Sect.</hi> 2.) unfitly argue againſt <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clus,</hi> That <hi>Nature</hi> is a <hi>Sublunary power;</hi> bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in this it differs from Nature, that the <hi>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verſall</hi> Circuit of Nature is never compre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hended; <hi>Nature</hi> being the <hi>Motus principium</hi> and <hi>Motion</hi> being above the <hi>Moon,</hi> no movin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thing can be equall in power with the <hi>Mover<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> but he ſaith truly, that this power is no ſeparated from the <hi>Celeſtiall</hi> bodies; that is diſtinct from thoſe powers from which the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> our affections proceed; wherefore, accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to their <hi>Power, Concurſion, Mixtion,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Alienation,</hi> it hath a diverſe <hi>Creation, Exiſtency</hi> and <hi>Diſſolution:</hi> What elſe is this, but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>motus principium</hi> to be in thoſe <hi>Celestials</hi> and that the <hi>Heavens</hi> have power to effect all things?</p>
               <p>Thus ſtrengthened therefore by the Authorities, I may preſume with <hi>Fernel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> the <hi>Phyſician</hi> an excellent <hi>Philoſopher (in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> de abd. rer. Cauſ.) gravem eorum eſſe ſtupid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> tatem, qui ſidera nihil in aera niſi calorem an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> frigus, imbres aut ſiccitatem lumine motu<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ducere
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:109298:42"/>
contendant;</hi> that ſuch are very igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nt, who would enforce upon the <hi>Stars</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ely a power over the <hi>Air,</hi> of cauſing Heat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Cold, Moyſture or Drought by their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight and Motion; if by their good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                     <desc>•••…</desc>
                  </gap>ution they do defend and preſerve the life <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f all things; why by their evill diſpoſition <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y they not diſcomodate the like? Thence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſay) is the firſt and chiefeſt health and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rvation of al things, thence alſo proceedeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ath: Thoſe therefore that are unskilfull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this <hi>Contemplation,</hi> do wholly abrogate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Cauſes</hi> and <hi>Powers;</hi> and deny them, as if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey were not, contrary to the teſtimonies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither are theſe <hi>(powers)</hi> received in the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ublunaries</hi> by that univerſall and equivocall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ower of the <hi>Heaven,</hi> which is drawn by all and every ſingular thing more or leſſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the various preparation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itution of their Nature, to which action <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey chiefly reſpect, and ſeem to govern over theſe <hi>Sublunaries</hi> by their Light and Motion: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or the ſame operation, and eſpecially of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his, and of every ſingular part of it (of ſuch the <hi>natures</hi> and <hi>ſpecies</hi> are for the moſt part diverſe) cannot be denyed to be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by their <hi>Influence</hi> and <hi>Aſpect.</hi> Neither do the virtue or ſpirit of the <hi>Celeſtiall</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies alwayes perform their work by inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixing
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:109298:43"/>
at the riſing of the <hi>Sun,</hi> at what time the <hi>Cock</hi> is obſerved more earneſtly to crow; which alteration the nature of the <hi>Cock</hi> doth more ſenſibly and accurately appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend then any other Creature, becauſe in the <hi>ſeries</hi> of things every one hath its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency from a certain <hi>Star;</hi> the <hi>Cock</hi> is properly and eſpecially conſtituted in the <hi>Solary</hi> order.</p>
               <p>In which ſenſe the opinion of the <hi>Saracens</hi> would not be ſo ridiculous and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible, who feign that there is a great <hi>Cock</hi> in <hi>Heaven,</hi> whoſe Crowing other <hi>Cocks</hi> here on <hi>Earth</hi> do only hear, and indeavour to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate as often as they hear him Crow. And that of <hi>Plato</hi> I conceive in the ſame ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that in the Earth the <hi>Celeſtiall</hi> bodies are in a <hi>Terreſtriall</hi> condition, and in <hi>heaven</hi> the <hi>Terreſtriall</hi> bodies are in a <hi>Celeſtiall</hi> dignity, &amp;c. Alſo according to the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy</hi> of the <hi>Pythagarians,</hi> the <hi>Stars</hi> are great <hi>Syſtems</hi> containing in themſelves whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver we have in the <hi>Syſtems</hi> or compaſſe of the <hi>Earth, Aire,</hi> and <hi>Water:</hi> To which that of <hi>Paracelſus agreeth in Tract.</hi> 1. <hi>de peſtili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Auſe dem <hi>Syder</hi> iſchen Leben ent ſpringet daſh Thieriſche Leben deſe Menſchen, alle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> matu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tieh auſs Eigentſchafft und Krafft deſs Himmels, Als i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r ſehet an dem Haan, der ſchreyet die Mitternacht und den Tagan,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:109298:43"/>
das compt ihm alles auſs dem Geſtirn, Bie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>un der Haan, alſo auch der Menſch.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>From the <hi>Sydereall</hi> life ariſeth the <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ll</hi> life; all which is naturall from the <hi>Celeſtiall</hi> property and quality: An exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple you ſee by the <hi>Cock,</hi> who giveth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the midnight, and for the break of day; which <hi>inſtinct</hi> he hath from <hi>Aſtralls: Man</hi> is in the ſame condition with the <hi>Cock.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For there is a double <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>Eſſence</hi> in Man, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the <hi>body,</hi> and the life; the one is quickned and governed by the inſpiration of the <hi>Heavens,</hi> the other followeth the nature of the <hi>Elements:</hi> This is not only affirmed by <hi>Iamblichus</hi> and <hi>Julianus,</hi> but by all others that have ſtudied this <hi>particuler, in Sole omnes coeleſtium eſſe virtutes,</hi> that in the <hi>Sun</hi> is all the virtues of the <hi>Celeſtiall</hi> bodies: And <hi>Proclus</hi> ſaith, that all the virtues of the <hi>Celeſtialls,</hi> do meet and are congregated into one body according to the <hi>Aſpect</hi> of the <hi>Sun.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now let us ſpeak of the <hi>Moon,</hi> with whom the bodies of <hi>Oyſters, Cockles,</hi> and all ſhell Fiſh, do equally increaſe and decreaſe; and <hi>Timber</hi> felled out of woods, when the <hi>Moon</hi> increaſeth and waxeth very light by reaſon of an acceſſion of <hi>moisture</hi> wither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and rotteth; but being cut down when
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:109298:44"/>
of <hi>humours,</hi> and commotion in the <hi>Member,</hi> either it workes not with a body of leſſe activity, or is hindered by the indiſpoſition of the ſubject. I have obſerved (ſayes <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilius</hi>) that <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ☌ ♀ doth move <hi>Phyſick</hi> very little. But concerning the particular qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of the <hi>Moon;</hi> ſee <hi>Macrobius in Septimo Saturnal.</hi> towards the end; <hi>Gualterus Ryff, in Iatro-mathematica;</hi> and <hi>Antonius Maginus de legitimo Aſtronomiae in Medicina uſu; Theophra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus in lib. de Tempore;</hi> and <hi>Carrichterus;</hi> in all which, you may ſufficiently be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfyed.</p>
               <p>Theſe and many other Experiments doe not only prove the <hi>Solary</hi> and <hi>Lunary</hi> power, but alſo that al <hi>ſublunary</hi> things (in what kind ſoever conſtituted) are ſubject to the <hi>Stars,</hi> and that they borrow their obſcure and imperceptible virtues from other <hi>Planets</hi> and <hi>Stars:</hi> And it is affirmed by the moſt <hi>learned,</hi> that ſuch is the conſtitution of the <hi>Heavens,</hi> chiefly from the various permixtion of the <hi>Planets,</hi> the cauſe of proper motion (as hath been formerly delivered) both men and horſes, and all kind of perfect <hi>Animals,</hi> are generated from the very <hi>Elements,</hi> as from the moſt conjunct and adjacent <hi>matter:</hi> And likewiſe the more imperfect <hi>Animals</hi> as <hi>Mice, Frogs, Flies,</hi> &amp;c. (which by obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) are generated of their own accord,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:109298:44"/>
as it were in a moment, yet <hi>time</hi> hath here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e firſt and chiefeſt part; and many other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ings which we have mentioned are not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>fected or produced but in their certain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me; which the <hi>Preacher</hi> confeſſeth (<hi>Eccleſiaſtes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ap.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 1.) <hi>To all things there is an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ointed</hi> time <hi>and a</hi> time <hi>to every purpoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nder the Heaven;</hi> which he manifeſteth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y a Catalogue of Examples, fitly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lying that to every ſigular and appointed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing.</p>
               <p>Therefore the naturall <hi>Philoſophers</hi> have wiſely ſaid <hi>Motus et actionis eandem eſſe</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d tempus qualis ſit corporis ipſius ad locum &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>empus.</hi> There is the ſame relation of <hi>motion</hi> and <hi>action</hi> unto time, as there is of the body <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſelf unto <hi>place</hi> and <hi>time:</hi> To which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion <hi>Hippocrates</hi> conſenteth (in <hi>Epidem.</hi> 2. <hi>Sect.</hi> 6.) ſaying all things have a <hi>ſolution</hi> like to the <hi>ſolution</hi> of the <hi>voice,</hi> and every one of theſe are diſſolved in a certain <hi>time;</hi> for from whence is the menſuration of <hi>time</hi> but from the <hi>heavens?</hi> Therefore their power is in the <hi>Celeſtiall cauſes;</hi> as in <hi>ſeeds</hi> the power of thoſe things which proceed from them are in them; and the <hi>Effectrices</hi> of the moſt eminent mutations, are not only in the Elementary nature, but in other things having a more noble <hi>originall:</hi> In which ſenſe I underſtand that of <hi>Oſea, (cap.</hi>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:109298:45"/>
2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. &amp; 22.) confirming the golden Chain of <hi>nature;</hi> And in that day (ſaith the Lord) I will hear the <hi>Heavens,</hi> and they ſhall hear the <hi>Earth,</hi> and the Earth ſhall hear the Corne, and the Wine, and the Oil, and they ſhall hear <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The heavens (I ſay) next to the firſt cauſe is the <hi>Centre, beginning, ſeminary, Architect</hi> and <hi>Archetype</hi> of all naturall things; this ſame reconciles the firſt with the laſt, and the ſupremeſt with the middle and loweſt, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſalls with particulars, diverſities with diverſities, contraries with contraries, like with like, joyneth, faſhioneth, and perfecteth all things with all things, by a certain naturall law, (but much obſcured from us by reaſon of its too much remote variety) as you may ſafely confeſſe, acknowledge and maintain, that all viſible things are the worke, fruit, effect, off-ſpring, and power of <hi>Heaven,</hi> under whatſoever name or notion they are related to it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:109298:45"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of the Time deſtinated by the <hi>Heavens</hi> for the propoſed Operations.</head>
               <p>SEEing therefore the power of the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly</hi> bodies is ſo ample, according to the various ejaculations of their <hi>virtues;</hi> in which reſpect, the Philoſopher (<hi>in</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
                  <hi>Phyſicorum</hi>) confeſſeth the <hi>Superiour</hi> bodies to be as the <hi>forms</hi> of thoſe things which are contained in them; and all the <hi>ſubſtances, facies,</hi> and <hi>powers</hi> of <hi>Terrene</hi> things, depend on their affimilative countenance; which <hi>Scaliger</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly concludeth, with us; whether the World had a <hi>beginning,</hi> or is <hi>Eternall:</hi> And <hi>Plato</hi> teacheth that the proper <hi>ſeries</hi> of things, even to the laſt, dependeth on every <hi>Star:</hi> This truly may very well be ſaid, that the Condition of the <hi>Heavens</hi> doe very much contribute to all kinde of propoſed actions, upon whoſe favourable <hi>influence</hi> chiefly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends our <hi>diſpoſitions.</hi> But becauſe we are not more ignorant of any thing, then of thoſe which appertaine to the <hi>Heavens,</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> himſelf teſtifieth (38. <hi>cap.</hi>) in theſe words, <hi>Knoweſt thou the Ordinances of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? Canſt thou ſet the Dominion thereof in the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:109298:46"/>
Earth?</hi> therefore we will (though weakly ſumme up ſome particulars relating he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unto: Wherefore, in theſe operatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wherein the heart and vitall ſpirit a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Clients,</hi> the fortunate and powerfull <hi>Sun</hi> to be choſen for their <hi>Patron,</hi> and to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Moon</hi> opportunely directed: Let the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> therefore be in the <hi>Angle</hi> of the <hi>Eaſt</hi> or <hi>We<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> or of the <hi>Angles</hi> of either of the <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> heavens,</hi> but chiefly in the <hi>Angle</hi> of the <hi>Aſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant</hi> or of the <hi>Tenth</hi> houſe, having the <hi>medi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Coeli</hi> above it, or at leaſt in the <hi>Plagis</hi> (o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Cadent</hi>) which next ſucceeds the <hi>Angle:</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, under the Signes ♈ or ♌, but chiefly under ♌ the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> beholding him; for it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obſerved, that then the <hi>ſpirit</hi> doth ſo vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, that it may be able to reſiſt the <hi>peſtile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall</hi> poyſon; which <hi>Marſilius</hi> reporteth to appear plainly in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and <hi>Aegypt,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Regions</hi> that are under ♌, where, when the ☉ enters ♌, the <hi>Pestilence</hi> cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth.</p>
               <p>You may likewiſe obſerve, that when ♃ beholdeth ☉ in a <g ref="char:trine">△</g> or ⚹, or at leaſt, when the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> proceedeth from the <hi>Aſpect</hi> of one to behold another; eſpecially, when ſhe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth from the <hi>Aſpect</hi> of the ☉ to ☌ ♃, for <hi>Ptolemy</hi> hath taught, that ♃ doth moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly agree with the ☉: As the <hi>Manſions</hi> of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in a <hi>fiery</hi> Signe, namely, in ♈, ♌, or
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:109298:46"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhe fortunately <hi>aſpecteth</hi> ♃ &amp; ☉: Alſo, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> applying of <hi>Cordiall</hi> things <hi>internally</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ternally</hi> to the heart, is very expedient; and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dyet</hi> of ſubtle aliments (or of eaſie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtion) being very wholſome and nutrimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll; a frequent and gentle <hi>motion,</hi> a cleer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd temperate <hi>Ayre,</hi> eſpecially a cheerfull <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>art.</hi> The <hi>Naturall virtue</hi> is governed by ♃ participating with ♀ &amp; <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>; but when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>trength is to bee increaſed in the <hi>geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>als,</hi> the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> &amp; ♀ are to be choſen, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> makes a man <hi>fruitfull</hi> and <hi>chearfull,</hi> and when therefore ſhe is either with the ☉ or ♃, ſhe is a fortunate <hi>Aſpect:</hi> The ſame is likewiſe to be underſtood of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe muſt not be in the <hi>Ecliptick,</hi> nor within the <hi>Rayes</hi> of the ☉ by 12 <hi>degrees,</hi> unleſſe by chance ſhe be at the ſame <hi>minute</hi> in ☌ with the ☉: Neither muſt ſhe be in her <hi>detriment,</hi> or hindred by ♄ or ♂ nor in ☍ with ☉, nor diminiſhed in <hi>light,</hi> nor in her <hi>ſlow</hi> courſe, ſhe muſt not be <hi>combuſt</hi> in her way, nor in the <hi>Eight, Sixth,</hi> or <hi>Ninth</hi> houſe, nor in the bounds of ♂ or ♄. Neither muſt ſhe be found in any of the barren Signes of ♋, ♍, or ♑: But if you cannot obſerve theſe things, however take notice of ♃ or ♀ in the <hi>Aſcendant,</hi> or <hi>medium Coeli,</hi> for ſo they come under the <hi>detriments</hi> of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, and let her behold ♃ or ♀ by a <g ref="char:trine">△</g> or ⚹ <hi>Aſpect:</hi> But
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:109298:47"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Talis mens hominum, qualem Pater ipſe Deorum,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Atque hominum adducit.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Such are our mindes, and ſuch they muſt be, when</l>
                        <l>Govern'd by <hi>Jove</hi> the Father of Gods and Men.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jupiter</hi> hath ſo great a power over the <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal</hi> or <hi>Vital</hi> ſpirit, that he is ſaid, with a <hi>Wand</hi> to Charm and Excite the minde of Man; by which they would inferre, that he is able by his <hi>Aſpect</hi> or otherwiſe, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to Dull and Debilitate, other time<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to Quicken and Corroborate the <hi>diſpoſition</hi> of Men.</p>
               <p>In all theſe things <hi>Jupiter</hi> is to be looked upon, in reſpect of a certain <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; in which one, we may conclude the faculties of the other <hi>Celeſtiall:</hi> Alſo the <hi>member</hi> of the body is to be obſerved, and what <hi>Signes</hi> govern the infected Member, and be carefull that the <hi>Luminaries</hi> be found in the Signe governing the Member; or at<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leaſt wiſe, that ſuch a Signe aſcends the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern <hi>Horizon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if you can get neither of theſe, it will ſuffice if the <hi>Moon</hi> be found in the Signe of the ſame <hi>Quadrant;</hi> but in the interim, not
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:109298:47"/>
neglecting the <hi>houres</hi> of the <hi>Planets</hi> (as they all them): Laſtly, in whatſoever diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion you elect their addicted <hi>Planets,</hi> let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t be either in the <hi>Aſcendant,</hi> or in a good <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>guration</hi> to it.</p>
               <p>The power of which <hi>Planets</hi> over certain Diſeaſes, <hi>Maginus</hi> doth largely treat <hi>(in lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g. Aſtrologiae in Medicinae uſu):</hi> It ſhall ſuffice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or the Concluſion of this Chapter to ſet down one or two examples:</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Magneticall</hi> Cure of the <hi>Eyes:</hi> Let ♃ be taken in the <hi>Aſcendant,</hi> or in a good place neer unto it, for the time of <hi>tranſplanting</hi> of <hi>Mumie,</hi> which is the principall matter; and take heed of <hi>Conſtellations</hi> hurtfull to the Lyes; (of which <hi>Maginus</hi> in <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>lib. d.</hi>) Neither muſt the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be in <hi>Earthly</hi> Signes, or joyned with ♂, but rather in ♈: ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe obſerve the other <hi>Patrons</hi> of this ſenſe.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Dropſie;</hi> when the <hi>Mumie</hi> is to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xtracted, let the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be in <hi>Watry</hi> Signes, not with too powerfull ♃, nor when he is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally in ☌ with her: But when it is to be ſet in the Earth and tranſplanted, let ♃ be then in his higheſt <hi>dignities,</hi> either in ♋, ♐, or ♍; or if in none of theſe, let the Signs themſelves be in the Eaſtern <hi>Aſcendant;</hi> let the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be <hi>decreaſing,</hi> diminiſhing in <hi>light;</hi> or at leaſtwiſe, let her be happily directed to the ☉ or ♂, which though it bee more
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:109298:48"/>
would be too long in this place to relate) and let him procure <hi>ſweat</hi> by the motion of his body, ſtill retaining the <hi>Magnetical Earth;</hi> then, having mixt it with a little <hi>new</hi> and <hi>fertile Earth,</hi> put in it the <hi>ſeed</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Magerome,</hi> of <hi>Table-rayall,</hi> or of <hi>Spike,</hi> and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> other hearbs proper for the <hi>Brain:</hi> Afterward let them thus grow in the open Aire, and the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of the <hi>Brain</hi> will ſo be <hi>tranſplanted,</hi> and wil wonderfully vegetate with the <hi>Plant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In like manner, you muſt order the <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neticall Earth</hi> ſtrengthened with the <hi>Mumie</hi> of the <hi>Heart,</hi> mingled with ſimple and pure <hi>Earth;</hi> and put in it <hi>ſeeds</hi> of <hi>Cordiall</hi> hearbs, as <hi>Mint, Burrage, Bugloſſe,</hi> or the like.</p>
               <p>But the third, which exhauſteth the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of the <hi>Liver,</hi> (being mixed with pure <hi>Earth</hi> before) put in to it <hi>Hepatick, Splenetick,</hi> and <hi>Nephritick</hi> Plants; namely, <hi>Carduus Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictus, Avens,</hi> (or <hi>Bennet) Roſemary,</hi> Seed of <hi>Ononis,</hi> (or <hi>Resbarrow) &amp;c.</hi> and the <hi>ſpirits</hi> likewiſe of the ſame parts will betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to it: Mingle theſe 3 <hi>plants</hi> or <hi>fruits</hi> in a <hi>Cucurbite,</hi> and extract their <hi>Eſſences</hi> by the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of Wine: which <hi>Eſſence</hi> give to any one whoſe favour you deſire, in any thing you pleaſe; and ſo the <hi>Mumiall</hi> ſpirit <hi>extracted</hi> wil preſently paſſe into its appropriated places, and become <hi>homogeneall</hi> and conformable to them: Hence proceedeth the ſame minde,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:109298:48"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſame affection in all things, by reaſon of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is union of <hi>Concordancy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if the <hi>Mumie</hi> ſhall be extracted onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om the <hi>Brain,</hi> then they will wonderfully <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gree in their <hi>minde, intellect,</hi> or <hi>ſpirit</hi> and <hi>vital</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>culty proceeding from the <hi>Brain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If from the <hi>Heart,</hi> they will be conjoyned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> their <hi>vital</hi> ſpirit and faculty proceeding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>om the <hi>Heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If from the <hi>Liver,</hi> and other inferiour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>embers, then they will <hi>ſympathiſe</hi> in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>irit, or <hi>natural,</hi> or <hi>concupiſcible</hi> and <hi>appetive</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>culty, and in other ſubordinate things.</p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Mumies</hi> of the Three principall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>embers, or the <hi>Eſſences</hi> of them being gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n, as they occaſion a ſingular Union of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ncordancy,</hi> and a perpetuall Conformity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ereof; ſo alſo do they cauſe <hi>love,</hi> and a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſt abſolute degree of <hi>friendſhip;</hi> for every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing is moſt inclinable to that which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſt like it ſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:109298:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> To reconcile private or publick <hi>Enemies.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis hath (in a manner) the ſame effect as the Three <hi>Mumies</hi> treated of in the precedent Chapter, this onely excepted, (to wit) that the <hi>Mumie</hi> muſt be <hi>extracted</hi> from both <hi>parties,</hi> and likewiſe adminiſtred to <hi>both;</hi> for if any one ſhould give his owne <hi>Mumie</hi> to his Enemy, he would be incited in a love towards him, inſomuch that he would courteouſly preſent his affection<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to him, but the other would ungratefully decline him, nay, he would never deſiſt from a deadly and inveterate hatred towards him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore, in this it muſt be endeavoured that a <hi>mutuall</hi> Concordancy be made, and that with <hi>equall</hi> paſſion; therefore, the <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> of both perſons muſt be taken and in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>termingled with ſome kinde of <hi>fertile Earth,</hi> and <hi>implanted</hi> into an hearb moſt proper for ſuch an operation; and then to be indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently adminiſtred to both.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:109298:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o reconcile the <hi>Ape</hi> and <hi>Serpent</hi> (na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally hating one another) and other <hi>Animals,</hi> who are by nature enemies.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THeophr. Paracelſus in lib. de Tempore</hi> (beſides other Authors) doth write <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at <hi>Apes</hi> and <hi>Serpents</hi> do (with a certain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cret and more then <hi>Vatinian</hi> hatred) mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly proſecute each other; and although <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is be naturall to them, as to <hi>Scorpions</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd <hi>Mice, Serpents</hi> and <hi>Cancers,</hi> the <hi>Lyon</hi> and <hi>Cock, Cock</hi> and <hi>Buzzard, Wolves</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heep,</hi> (whoſe skins made into Drums <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oe <hi>antipathize</hi>) which (beſides <hi>Boetius</hi> and <hi>Opianus) Homer</hi> teſtifyeth <hi>lib.</hi> 22. <hi>Iliad:</hi>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The Wolfe and Lambe do ever diſagree</l>
                        <l>Among themſelves, through their Antipathie.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:109298:50"/>Yet may that <hi>enmity</hi> be admirably com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by means of this <hi>Tranſplantation</hi> (ſo much commended) and in ſtead thereof a wonderfull <hi>Complacency</hi> may be had. And the ſame may likewiſe be effected in all Creatures any way diſcenting among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as by this plainely appeareth; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the force and power of this <hi>Myſticall Philoſophy,</hi> doth penetrate the very <hi>principall</hi> of Nature; ſo that nothing can be ſo naturall or obſtinately <hi>inherent,</hi> but may be extirpated; or corrected, by this <hi>contrary</hi> of the ſame nature.</p>
               <p>But to proceed to the ſcope of the <hi>matter</hi> aforeſaid; In the firſt place, let the <hi>ſpermes</hi> be collected with all the care as may be, and mingled together, nouriſhing them with a certain refined and fertile <hi>Earth;</hi> then let them be divided into two parts, <hi>(viz.)</hi> in one part, the nutriment of the <hi>Ape, Sheep, Cock;</hi> in the other part, of the <hi>Serpent, Wolfe, Hauke,</hi> &amp;c. let it be <hi>inſeminated,</hi> &amp;c. Afterward let the <hi>accreſcency</hi> (or fruit) be given mutually to the Creatures to eate.</p>
               <p>To this chiefly pertaineth that admired gentleneſſe of ſome wilde <hi>Beaſts</hi> and brute <hi>Animals</hi> which naturally fly from <hi>Man;</hi> ſo that oftentimes it is ſeen, that the moſt ſavage Beaſts become tame and tractable,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:109298:50"/>
as <hi>Nazianzen (in carmine ſacro,</hi> or his <hi>Divine Poem,</hi>) in which (precepts to Virgins) he writeth, that he himſelfe hath ſeen a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>Lyon</hi>-keeper, riding on a <hi>Lyon,</hi> who being trained up to it hath like an horſe patiently endured the bridle; Which <hi>Virgill</hi> affirmeth in <hi>Aeneid.</hi> 3.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et juncti currum Domini ſubiere Leones.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lyons</hi> were joyn'd with one accord,</l>
                     <l>To draw the Chariots of their Lord.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>This hath likewiſe been experienced by thoſe who have triumphed in <hi>Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots</hi> drawn with <hi>Tigers;</hi> which <hi>Silius</hi> alſo witneſſeth in <hi>lib.</hi> 17. <hi>Of the Carthaginian War.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>— <hi>Odoratis deſcendens Liber ab Indis</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Egit Pampineos fraenata Tigride currus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>From the ſweet Indies did deſcend amain</l>
                     <l>Driving a <hi>Tigre</hi> in his branched wain.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>Martial, <hi>of the tamed</hi> Tigre.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Lambere ſecuri dextram conſueta Magiſtri</l>
                  <l>Tigris ab Hyrcano gloria prima jugo.</l>
               </q>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:109298:51"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> To procure a mutuall love and affection betwixt a <hi>Man</hi> and his <hi>Wife.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis uſe of <hi>Mumie</hi> is related to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, only this muſt be eſpecially ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, (which for many reaſons I modeſtly referre to the more prudent as followeth) <hi>Quod ſi</hi> Maritus <hi>uxori ſuam mumiam paret, loco herbarum Renibus dicatarum, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>terinas eligere neceſſe ſit, quales ſunt: Valeriana, Roſmarinus, Satureja, Arthemiſia, Satyrion foemina, &amp;c. Virtus enim appetitiva erga viros, quatenus in</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>conſtituta eſt, faeminis in matrice ſituatur; Proinde Spiritus Mumiae appetitivae Epatis &amp; Renum Virilium in praedictas herbas uterinas tranſplantetur, ut ita ductu earundem Spiritus Mumiae Maſculae in locum a natura praemon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratum, matricem nempe feliciter dirigatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quod ſi vero</hi> Uxor <hi>marito eandem intentant, loco uterinarum plantis, Seminibuſve, membris vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilibus naturali proprietate dicatis utatur, Satyrio nempe maſculo, caepis &amp; ſimilibus; minime gentium vero menſtruo, quouſque tamen audaciae non raro ab improbis &amp; incautis meretriculis perventum. Illud enim abſque dubio deleterium eſt, citam mortem inferens. Et quanquam Sperma virile &amp; foemineum
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:109298:51"/>
in plantam quandam tranſlata, eo quo diſtum eſt modo &amp; artificio, pares effectus edant, divina tamen lege illud prorſus interdictum Proinde ad uſum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictum illa in ſubſtantia minime revocentur; Quin potius, ubi opus eſt, Spiritus eorundem terrae Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neticae beneficio e lumbis extrahatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet I intend not this <hi>Myſtery</hi> ſhould be common to all, or that it ſhould be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by wicked perſons, though ſuch an action may be done to a laudable and good end, where the <hi>Husband</hi> may the more affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onately enjoy his <hi>Wife,</hi> according to the bond of <hi>Matrimony,</hi> or where the <hi>Husband</hi> deſireth it for <hi>propagation</hi> ſake, which cannot be obtained by reaſon of diſcord from his <hi>wife;</hi> in which caſe the <hi>Husband</hi> may with a ſafe conſcience <hi>meliorate</hi> her nature, and make it more tractable by his <hi>Mumie:</hi> And this Extraction of his <hi>Mumie</hi> according to the moſt learned Profeſſors of this <hi>Philoſophy</hi> muſt be done under the <hi>Exaltation</hi> of ♀ and when ſhe is happily <hi>aſpected</hi> with the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> &amp; ♃, (as I have formerly noted.)</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:109298:52"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> To cure both ſorts of <hi>Jaundies.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the firſt place be ſure of the <hi>Mumie</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted from the three principall <hi>members</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that thereby the whole <hi>Mumiall ſpirit</hi> may in ſome meaſure be in your power; (for the <hi>Jaundies</hi> is diſperſed through the whole body) let it be <hi>implanted</hi> into the ſeed of <hi>Line, Nock-weed, Celandine,</hi> or into ſome other that is proper to the <hi>Jaundies,</hi> let <hi>Onyſoi</hi> (by ſome called <hi>Aſſelli</hi>) or the liquor of them, be given to the Patient; into which they being laid in any veſſell in hot water are reſolved: Or laſtly, the <hi>excrements</hi> or dung of Geeſe diſſolved in wine, or <hi>Juniper-berries;</hi> for by meanes of all theſe that <hi>colorated</hi> humor is preternaturally voided by the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine:</hi> With this <hi>Mumiated</hi> urine, water every morning the <hi>Magneticall Earth,</hi> and the ſeeds contained in it; Afterward the ſeeds beginning to grow, the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of the <hi>Jaundiſe</hi> will be fully transferred into the <hi>plant;</hi> which with all the <hi>Mumiated</hi> Earth you may af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward caſt into a <hi>River,</hi> or hang it up in a Chimny to be dryed; either of which is to be obſerved according to the diſpoſition and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:109298:52"/>
conſtitution of the body, whoſe health is by his meanes deſired; for if the body be <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lethorical</hi> (ſomewhat inclining to a <hi>Dropſie) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſeed</hi> is to be hung up in the <hi>Smoak;</hi> but <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſqualid</hi> and <hi>dry,</hi> it muſt be caſt into the <hi>water.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y this <hi>Art</hi> there is no kind of <hi>Jaundies</hi> though otherwiſe incurable) but may here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d remedy; which may be proved even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this common experience: It is uſuall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> take <hi>horſes dung,</hi> ſome three or foure clods, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on which the patient having made water <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce before, it is to be tyed in a bladder or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nnen cloth, and hung up in a Chimny to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y, and afterward caſt into the fire: This experience hath oftentimes been found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uccceſſefull in curing the diſeaſe afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:109298:53"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> To cure <hi>Feavers</hi> by this <hi>Myſtery.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALthough the beſt and ſureſt way of curing <hi>Feavers,</hi> is by <hi>diaceltateſſon Opo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyron,</hi> although the matter (through the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of the <hi>Phyſician</hi>) be moſt perfectly dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated by opening a <hi>vein;</hi> Notwithſtanding this ſhall (likewiſe) ſomewhere be very uſefull.</p>
               <p>Here therefore the <hi>Mumie,</hi> both <hi>vitall</hi> and <hi>naturall,</hi> muſt be extracted, in the place and manner as aforeſaid; yea, I could adviſe it might be from the <hi>Arteries;</hi> this being done, afterward mixe it with hearbs good for the blood and reſiſting putrefaction; hearbs proper for this uſe are <hi>Nettles, Fumentary, Celandine</hi> (the great) <hi>Century, Balme, Mint, Germander;</hi> let <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine</hi> be provoked by the falt of <hi>Nettles,</hi> or <hi>Sage,</hi> or <hi>Juniper-berries;</hi> with which <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine,</hi> the <hi>Magneticall Earth</hi> muſt afterwards be duely watered; and the <hi>accreſcency</hi> of them muſt either be caſt into the <hi>water</hi> or dryed in the <hi>Aire,</hi> with which the <hi>Feaver</hi> will preſently conſume as the ſame ſhall periſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:109298:53"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> Of the Oppilations of the <hi>Liver, Brain, Lungs, Spleen, Reynes, &amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt extract the <hi>Mumie</hi> naturally anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the affected part; then let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e former <hi>Tranſplantation</hi> into hearbs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>propriated to them follow; (for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ple)</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Liver</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Braine</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Lungs</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Spleen</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Reynes</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
be infected then <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant</hi> it into
<list>
                     <item>Rue, Liverwort, Maiden haire.</item>
                     <item>Sweet Marjoram, Bears-foot, Rue, Serpyllum.</item>
                     <item>Nettles, Vernacle, Lung-wort.</item>
                     <item>Stone-wort, Hedg-nettle, Germander.</item>
                     <item>Reſtbarrow, Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den red, Parſly, Gromell, &amp;c.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Let <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine</hi> be provoked by <hi>Salt</hi> of theſe hearbs artificially prepared; with which the <hi>Magneticall Earth</hi> muſt be watered to</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:109298:54"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXII.</hi> Of <hi>Wounds</hi> and <hi>Ulcers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt, (as before) take the <hi>Mumie</hi> from the places affected, into which muſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeminated by way of <hi>Tranſplantation,</hi> either ſpotted <hi>Arſmart</hi> or <hi>Comfrey,</hi> or other hearbs favouring the affected parts; Let <hi>urin</hi> be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked by <hi>Tartar,</hi> with which the <hi>Mumiated Earth</hi> is to be watred for its better nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: then let the <hi>accreſcency</hi> be dryed in the <hi>Aire,</hi> and ſo the Diſeaſe will undoubtedly be cured.</p>
               <p>Where you muſt alſo note, that this Cure is oftentimes performed by the <hi>Mumiall Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netiſme,</hi> although the <hi>extraction</hi> of <hi>Mumie</hi> doth not alwayes intercede: for in ſome caſes it happeneth, that the <hi>weapon</hi> or inſtrument that gave the wound partaketh of the tacted <hi>Mumie,</hi> without the direction of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>Medicine,</hi> eſpecially when it hath remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned long in the wounded part; for any thing that continueth long in the wounds, as a <hi>Knife, Nail, Glaſſe,</hi> is of much leſſe force in a ſudden <hi>tranſition,</hi> ſeeing ſuch ſhort time can ſcarcely produce any effect: Or laſtly, where it is imbrewed in blood by a delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:109298:54"/>
                  <hi>tranſmiſſion,</hi> or by any retention of that place: And ſo it ſerveth in ſtead of Artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>extraction,</hi> ſome part of the <hi>Mumie</hi> being thus compendiouſly <hi>attracted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore when any one is either <hi>hurt, wounded,</hi> or otherwiſe prejudiced in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Let the <hi>Dart, Knife,</hi> or <hi>Sword</hi> be thruſt into the <hi>Earth,</hi> (which is the Mother, and (as it were) potentative <hi>genericall</hi> branch of all <hi>Balſams,</hi> (although by this reaſon that operation is of little worth) that the <hi>Mumial ſpirit</hi> adhering to the Weapon may not <hi>evapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate;</hi> in the mean time, let the wound be bound up with the root of <hi>Mead-ſaffron,</hi> pounded and mingled with 3 or 4 drops of <hi>Wine,</hi> or <hi>Vinegar,</hi> or the like, for a <hi>Plaiſter,</hi> but the <hi>excrements</hi> (by a certain myſtical virtue) is the beſt, or whatſoever is <hi>Balſamick</hi> and next at hand, the Weapon may be thruſt into, as <hi>Lard, Balſam, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguent, &amp;c.</hi> Yet here is chiefly to be reſpected, thoſe things which are of <hi>Mumie</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſnea,</hi> which indeed is the <hi>Sylloge</hi> and <hi>Collection</hi> of <hi>Mumial ſpirits,</hi> and alſo of the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of the World, by whoſe mediation the <hi>active</hi> and <hi>paſſive</hi> qualities do moſt happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concenter: Alſo, that which is by ſome obſerved, is no wayes abſurd, in <hi>Cacoethical</hi> (or ill diſpoſed) <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers,</hi> and old <hi>Fluxions</hi> which are continually running; that the <hi>ſanies</hi> of a Wound being anoynted with <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam</hi>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:109298:55"/>
or <hi>Weapon-ſalve,</hi> and incloſed in a Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhell, and afterward hung up in a dry place under a moyſt Air, will moſt effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally further the Cure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> Of the <hi>Hernia,</hi> or Burſtenneſſe.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, let the <hi>Mumie</hi> be <hi>extracted</hi> from the place <hi>affected,</hi> into which implant (as before) <hi>Symphytum majus,</hi> (or <hi>Walwort</hi> the greater) then hang it in the Air til it be dry; or (where, by means of the <hi>Mumial Magnes,</hi> the <hi>Mumie</hi> hath been rightly <hi>extracted</hi>) chooſe the <hi>Roſin</hi> tree, <hi>Cherry</hi> tree, <hi>Firre</hi> tree, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> let the <hi>Mumie</hi> be placed at the Root, the tree being ſlit through the middle, and the Clift ſo wide, that the ſick party may there conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently make his <hi>tranſmiſſion,</hi> which muſt be 3 times forward and backward, <hi>in nomine SS. Trinitatis, in quo merito omnia inchoanda &amp; perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienda:</hi> and that eſpecially in the hour and day of ♀: Let the Patient alſo freely voyd his <hi>urine</hi> upon the <hi>root</hi> of the tree; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done, let the tree be conveniently clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up with <hi>wax;</hi> ſo the <hi>Hernia</hi> (or Burſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe)
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:109298:55"/>
being never ſo monſtrous, having been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut into it as aforeſaid, wil in a ſhort time be moſt perfectly cured <hi>(quamvis alicubi nihil repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſita fuerit ſanata).</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIV.</hi> Of <hi>Fluxions</hi> and Salt <hi>Rheums</hi> cauſing pains and ſoreneſſe in the Teeth and Eyes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>EXtract</hi> the <hi>Mumie</hi> of the place offended, and let it be <hi>tranſplanted</hi> into ſpotted <hi>Arſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmart, &amp;c.</hi> Notwithſtanding the ſame may be done compendiouſly by the root of <hi>Ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſill</hi> plucked up with the whole hearb, and rubbing the aking teeth therewith till they bleed; then preſently ſetting the ſame <hi>root</hi> in the proper and native place wherein it was firſt plucked up, and ſo let it grow: Thus any ache or pain in the Teeth ſhall with great wonder be aſſwaged and cured.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:109298:56"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXV.</hi> Of <hi>Menſtruous Evacuation</hi> and <hi>Reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LEt the <hi>Mumie</hi> firſt be <hi>extracted</hi> from about the <hi>Hypocondria</hi> and <hi>Navill,</hi> which (after the uſuall manner) is to be <hi>implanted</hi> into <hi>Arſmart,</hi> then provoke <hi>urine</hi> by adminiſtring <hi>Peniroyall,</hi> with which wet the <hi>Mumiated</hi> Earth; then take the <hi>plant</hi> (growing to perfection) and either dry it in the Air, or burn it in the Fire.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Retention</hi> of <hi>Evacuations,</hi> let the <hi>Mumie</hi> be extracted from the ſame places, and likewiſe from about the <hi>Paps;</hi> then let it be <hi>inſeminated</hi> into <hi>Peniroyall,</hi> by which alſo <hi>urine</hi> muſt be provoked: Afterward, let the <hi>Excreſcency</hi> be caſt into the Water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:109298:56"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVI.</hi> Of the <hi>Conſumption</hi> &amp; <hi>Hectick Feaver.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>EXtract</hi> the <hi>Mumie</hi> from the 3 principall parts, and alſo from the <hi>ſpine</hi> of the <hi>back,</hi> and chief <hi>Muſcles</hi> of the body; <hi>implant</hi> it into <hi>Satyrion,</hi> and let them grow together, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ranſpoſe them into the <hi>Oak</hi> or <hi>Cherry</hi> tree; or elſe <hi>tranſplant</hi> the <hi>Mumie</hi> it ſelf into ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her of theſe, and the <hi>Patient</hi> ſhall amend in a ſhort time: Alſo, the <hi>Tincture</hi> of the <hi>Mumie</hi> of a ſound body adminiſtred to the ſick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon recovereth him: As I have delivered in another place.</p>
               <p>There is another reaſon of this <hi>Magnetiſme</hi> more commonly and eaſily practiſed, (as thus): Let a new laid Egge be boyled in the <hi>urine</hi> of the ſick party in a new Pipkin, (ſo as the urine may cleerly cover the Egge) let it boyl till the Egge be hard, then take out the Egge, and pierce it here and there, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſeeth it again in the ſame urine, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes turning it, till the urine be wholly conſumed; then let the Egg (being thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared) be buried in an <hi>Ant</hi> hill, and as the Egge conſumeth, ſo will the Diſeaſe, by a wonderfull ſympathy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:109298:57"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVII.</hi> Of particular <hi>Blaſtings.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis, according to the proceſſe of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Magnetiſme,</hi> hath nothing to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to it ſelf, onely that the <hi>Mumie</hi> is to be extracted from the inferior and ſuperior <hi>Articles,</hi> or joynts of the parts affected; and (that we may not (as they ſay) always harp on the ſame ſtring, but intermix ſome plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure with profit) we will here deliver a moſt excellent remedy againſt all Blaſtings, as well univerſal as particular, and indeed, a ſympathetical <hi>Magick</hi> from this very <hi>Art:</hi> This <hi>Amulet</hi> is a particle of the <hi>Coffin</hi> wherein a Woman in Childebed (dying through dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of <hi>Delivery</hi>) hath been put, and therei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> laid upon the <hi>ſpine</hi> of her back, and buried.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>vegetative</hi> augmentation, and <hi>nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritive</hi> faculty of the <hi>Childebed</hi> woman is prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally placed in the <hi>ſpine</hi> or bone of he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> back, and being laid in the <hi>Coffin,</hi> is now eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attracted, and aſſumed by a living body<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>ſymbolical</hi> and agreeable to its former ſubject.</p>
               <p>From this very <hi>foundation</hi> may a <hi>Childebed</hi> woman yet alive, and other <hi>Plethoricall</hi> and ſound perſons ſupply another with this fruitful and admirably nutritive <hi>Mumie,</hi> ſo that the <hi>Extraction</hi> be made from the <hi>ſpine</hi> of the back, the aforeſaid <hi>Magnes</hi> being laid
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:109298:57"/>
upon it; then <hi>implanted</hi> into proper hearbs; which hearbs muſt afterwards be taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly by the <hi>Patient:</hi> Thus truly there is no Diſeaſe ſo vehement or dangerous, but may have a remedy by this our practiſe; for that which ſeemeth moſt <hi>diſſentaneous,</hi> may (by this) be ſucceſſefully adapted and reconcil'd.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVIII.</hi> Againſt <hi>Sterlity</hi> or Barrenneſſe: And alſo the manner of detracting ſtrength from an <hi>Horſe,</hi> and tranſmitting it into a <hi>Man,</hi> or from any Man or Beaſt into any other.</head>
               <p>IT wil here be neceſſary to extract the <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> of the <hi>vital</hi> and <hi>natural</hi> faculty from the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ine</hi> of the back, under the <hi>Arm-pits</hi> and <hi>hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hondriis</hi> of any pregnant body; then <hi>tranſplant</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t into <hi>Satyrion,</hi> or (which ſome think bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er) into the common or black <hi>Thiſtle;</hi> and when it hath <hi>vegetated</hi> ſufficiently, give it to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <hi>barren</hi> party; which nevertheleſſe, that it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay be the more effectual, hang the ſaid herb with all the reſt about the parties neck; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ſhort time ſhe will prove as fruitfull as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y other.</p>
               <p>This I ſay (with Gods bleſſing) hath often been the happy means of much contentment
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:109298:58"/>
to <hi>Noble</hi> Families, before deſtitute of Heirs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>Neither doth this <hi>Art</hi> promiſe leſſe ſucceſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to thoſe that abſtract from a ſound body (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpeak not of men) the ſtrength of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> powers and faculties, and <hi>implant</hi> it in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: By the ſame <hi>Art,</hi> after this manner <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tract</hi> the <hi>Mumie</hi> from a <hi>ſound</hi> body perfectly in health, and <hi>implant</hi> it into the black <hi>Thiſtle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> which afterward may be adminiſtred to the <hi>ſick</hi> party; either in its <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> or reduced into its <hi>eſſence;</hi> let it be hung about thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> neck, and the <hi>ſick</hi> and <hi>infirm</hi> wil grow <hi>health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> and <hi>ſtrong.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the like manner alſo you may ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract the ſtrength from an <hi>Horſe</hi> and ſo tranſmit or infuſe it at pleaſure into a <hi>Man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Mingle the <hi>ſperm</hi> of the ſtrongeſt <hi>Horſes</hi> wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pure <hi>Earth, implant</hi> it into the black <hi>Thiſtle;</hi> when it is grown to its juſt bigneſſe, admini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter it to the <hi>party</hi> whoſe ſtrength you woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> increaſe; let it be hung about his <hi>neck</hi> and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſtrong Horſes <hi>languiſh</hi> the Party wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſtrengthen:</hi> But you muſt take notice, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aforeſaid <hi>root</hi> is to be <hi>implanted</hi> preſently afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>New Moon,</hi> and taken up two or thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dayes before the <hi>New Moon:</hi> This is equall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſucceſſeful in other Beaſts, whoſe faculty i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> expedient to be communicated to Man, as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Learned in theſe <hi>myſteries</hi> ſhall more exactl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſider the occaſion</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:109298:58"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
